<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the taking of Carthagena by the French in the year 1697 containing all the particulars of that expedition, from their first setting out to their return into Brest / by Monsieur de Pointis, commander in chief ; illustrated with a large copper plate describing the situation of Carthagena and parts adjacent.</title>
            <title>Relation de l'expidition de Carthagene. English</title>
            <author>Pointis, Jean-Bernard-Louis Desjean, baron de, 1645-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35116</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15020691</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15020691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1576:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the taking of Carthagena by the French in the year 1697 containing all the particulars of that expedition, from their first setting out to their return into Brest / by Monsieur de Pointis, commander in chief ; illustrated with a large copper plate describing the situation of Carthagena and parts adjacent.</title>
                  <title>Relation de l'expidition de Carthagene. English</title>
                  <author>Pointis, Jean-Bernard-Louis Desjean, baron de, 1645-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 134 p., [1] leaf of folded plates : map.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Buckley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"French original, Amsterdam, 1698, pub. under title: Relation de l'expidition de Carthagene ..."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cartagena (Colombia) --  History --  Siege, 1697.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT Of the Taking of CARTHAGENA BY THE FRENCH, In the Year 1697. Containing all the Particulars of that Expedition, from their firſt ſetting out, to their return into <hi>BREST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Monſieur De Pointis,</hi> Commander in Chief.</p>
            <p>Illuſtrated with <hi>a large Copper Plate,</hi> Deſcribing the Situation of <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena</hi> and Parts adjacent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Buckley,</hi> at the <hi>Dolphin</hi> over-againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church, in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE City of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> (which now gives Title to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Government of the ſame Name, and is reckon'd a Province of <hi>New Granada;</hi> or, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſome Writers, of <hi>New Andaluzia;</hi> but by others is annex'd to the <hi>Golden Caſtille</hi>) was begun to be built in the Year <hi>1532.</hi> by <hi>Peter de Heredia,</hi> and was finiſhed by <hi>Georgio Robledo,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Eight Years after the Foundation was laid.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103058:3"/>The Situation of its Port was found ſo convenient for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleets, and ſuch Quantities of rich Merchandize were brought down near to it, by the Confluence of the great Rivers of <hi>Santa Martha</hi> and the <hi>Magdalena,</hi> that the Town en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in Wealth, Number of People, Stately Edifices, and in a Juriſdiction over Five or Six petty Cities, till in the Year <hi>1585,</hi> It was ſack'd by the Valour of a few <hi>Engliſh,</hi> under the Command of Sir <hi>Francis Drake:</hi> in a <hi>Reign,</hi> when the Publick Good and Honour of <hi>England</hi> was the chief Buſineſs at Court, and our Land enrich'd with the Spoils of our Proud <hi>Enemies;</hi> who were humbled by the Conduct of our Fleets abroad, and our Naval Applications at Home.</p>
            <p>But this City of <hi>Carthagena</hi> received a greater Blow (before it was perfectly repair'd) from Five Privateers, led on by a diſguſted <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who burnt the Place to Aſhes, after they had ſurpriz'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour aſleep, and ſeiz'd a mighty Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Yet, for all this, it rais'd its Head again, number'd above Twenty Thouſand Inhabitants (whereof Four Thouſand were
<pb facs="tcp:103058:3"/>
               <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the reſt <hi>Meſticoes</hi> and Slaves) and improv'd daily in Riches and Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, till taken by the <hi>French</hi> from <hi>Breſt,</hi> and the <hi>Bucaniers</hi> from <hi>Petit Guaves,</hi> who ſeverally plunder'd it; as is particularly related by Monſieur de <hi>Pointis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into ſuch a fatal Stupidity are a certain People (by Nature Brave, formerly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors and Heroes) of late degenerated, either from the ill Influences of their State, or Church, or both; that now they fall a Prey to every Invader, and even to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers, and Vagabonds: The Cauſes whereof are too manifeſt, and own'd by a judicious and honest Writer of their own Country, whoſe Senſe I ſhall here deliver.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable Taxes are multiply'd and entail'd upon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> under Pretence of making good Deficiencies and Funds of Interest: The Treaſury grown Monſtrous, either by obſtructing or diverting the Publick Aliment, and by contracting new Debts: The Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees themſelves conſpire to cheat in their ſeveral Stations; in order to advance
<pb facs="tcp:103058:4"/>
or ſupport their own Extravagancies: The Court Officers, Gabellers, and ſuch Swarms of mercenary Vermine are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, draining the very Blood of the People: The Standing Forces upon Free Quarter, the Shipping neglected, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons and Magazines very ill ſupply'd, most of the Governours and Men in Trust (like ſo many Vultures) griping whatever comes within the Catch of their Talons. Trade is diſcourag'd by ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly advantagious Loans, by high Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Indulto's, and other Impoſts. The Church is over-grown with Revenues, Inquiſitions and Dominion; all which have contributed to impoveriſh and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Maſs of the Body Politick, and to reduce it into the Figure, we now behold it in;</q> all over Rickets, with large Heads and wither'd Limbs, for want of a proportionable Circulation, and a due Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration.</p>
            <p>Theſe Chronical Diſtempers in the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Governments in <hi>Europe,</hi> have infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the rest in <hi>America,</hi> where their Weakneſs is diſcovered upon all Occaſions. Indeed Monſieur <hi>de Pointis</hi> carried Twenty times the Force that Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:103058:4"/>
or the Privateers after him, did; yet conſidering the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had frequent and very early Intelligence of the <hi>French</hi> Preparations, and of their Arrival in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> methinks their Defence was very Languid, and ſcarce credible to one unacquainted with their preſent Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which will produce the like Symptomes and bad Effects in any other Nation, that has the Misfortune to ſuck in the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagions.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> whoſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory is related to be very fruitful, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a little too moist by the violent and frequent Rains.</p>
            <p>The Journals of Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi>'s Voyages commend the Plenty and Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Fruits found there; Oranges, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, Limes, Guavo's, ſome Spices and Balſams, eſpecially a ſort of long Pepper, and the <hi>Tolu,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Carolus Cluſius, Franciſcus Ximenes, John de Laet, Margrave, Hernandes,</hi> and others, are brought from the adjacent Parts in great Quantities. Gold is waſh'd down by the Torrents from the Mountains, where ſome precious Stones are found.
<pb facs="tcp:103058:5"/>
In a Word, the Country is much the ſame with the neighbouring <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> which has been ſo well deſcribed by Mr. <hi>Ringroſe,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Raveneau de Luſſan,</hi> and more lately by Captain <hi>Dampier,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wafer,</hi> that nothing more need be ſaid here of this Part of the <hi>Terra Firma.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:103058:6"/>
                  <p>EXPLANATION</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <p>A. Cartagena</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>B. Hihimani</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>C. Fort S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lazare</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>D. Fort S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Croix</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>E. Fort of Boccachica</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>F. Redout at the entrance of the Baſin</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>G. the Trenches</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>H. a Battery of 6 Guns</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>I. a Battery of 3 Guns &amp; two Mortars</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>K. a Battery of 6 Guns &amp; one Mortar</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>L. a Battery of one Mortar in the high-way</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>M. a Battery of one Mortar in a little Island</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>N. Notre Dame de la Poupe</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>O. Lake of N. D. de La Poupe</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>P. the Place where the French landed their Troops</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>Q. their Artillery landed</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>R. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scepter</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>S. the Vermandois</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>T. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lewis</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>V. a Galliot Bombarding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> City</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>Y. a Galliot Bombarding Bocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chica.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>1. 2 Mortars battering Bocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chica</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>2. the Ships Anchoring before Boccachica</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>3. the Deſcent upon Bocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chica</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>4. the Deſcent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bucca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niers fruſtrated by the roughneſs of the Sea</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>5. two Spaniſh Veſsels burnt</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <p>6. the French Camp</p>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Scale of one Mile.</p>
                  <p>Sold by Sam: Buckley at the Dolphin in Fleet street London</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:103058:7"/>
                  <p>A DRAUGHT<hi> OF THE CITY OF </hi>CARTAGENA<hi> ITS HARBOUR AND FORTS</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:103058:8"/>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103058:9"/>
            <head>Monſ<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>DE POINTI</hi>'S ACCOUNT OF HIS EXPEDITION TO Carthagena, In the YEAR 1697.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign I had long ſince form'd, of a Naval Expedition, that might be both honourable and advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, was put off from time to time by intervening Accidents, although Monſ. <hi>Pontchartrain</hi> had received His Majeſty's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Project I had the Honour to preſent him; and had, likewiſe, obtained the Ships, Men, and Ammunitions, which I propoſed to take with me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103058:10"/>But at length, the laying up of the Fleet, brought by Count <hi>Chateau Renault</hi> from <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> leaving all the Marine, in a manner, idle; and the Meaſures I had taken with Treaſurer-General <hi>Vanolles,</hi> ſeeming to promiſe a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fond for the Expence, there appear'd no farther Obſtacles to the Execution of this Enterprize.</p>
            <p>Hereupon we propos'd our Deſign to the Publick; which was ſo generally lik'd, and People were ſo forward to bring in their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that <hi>Vanolles</hi> was not able to receive it faſt enough; inſomuch, that he fancy'd he ſhould be forc'd to refuſe ſeveral Perſons, by reaſon we had agreed upon the Sum, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to exceed it.</p>
            <p>But the Face of Affairs became ſoon altered; for the Peace being concluded with <hi>Savoy,</hi> made it hop'd, that it would ſuddenly be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a General One: And 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, that if the War ſhould be at an end, before I was under Sail, I ſhould be order'd to the contrary; and ſo the Money employ'd upon our Armament, would be infallibly loſt. And now People were ſo far from offering new Sums, that thoſe who had already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in the Deſign, would have been very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have withdrawn their Contributions.</p>
            <p>I could not inform every Body, That Count <hi>Maurepas,</hi> who was acquainted with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of our Project, had engag'd Monſ. <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> to ask his Majeſty, What ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103058:10"/>
be done with our Armament, in caſe the Peace ſhould be agreed upon? And that His Majeſty was pleas'd to anſwer, That I might go on with it; for, if the Peace ſhould be concluded, he would take Care to re-imburſe the Adventurers. And we were aſſur'd of this Favour, by an expreſs Article inſerted in the Margin of the Minutes of the Marine Council, that was held upon this Matter: Nevertheleſs, many Perſons conſidering, that the beſt which could happen, would be to receive their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney again, choſe rather to keep it in their Purſes.</p>
            <p>And beſides this Prejudice, the ill Succeſs of ſome Attempts that preceded mine, and from which great Matters were expected, diſcourag'd the Publick more than the appearance of an approaching Peace.</p>
            <p>By this means we were oblig'd to proceed upon the Fond that was already advanc'd, which was much inferiour to what I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; and this compell'd me to leſſen our Preparations, and conſequently weaken the Armament. However, being determin'd to go thorough with my Undertaking, I reſolv'd to make uſe of the Advantages which the Court was pleaſed to confer on me, in allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me ſuch conſiderable Succours. So I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Brest</hi> in the beginning of <hi>October,</hi> 1696; and to work we went, with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Diligence, to fit out our Fleet: But the bad Weather hinder'd our Careening; ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103058:11"/>
that we could not get out of <hi>Brest,</hi> but lay in that Road 'till the 6th of <hi>January;</hi> from whence my Project was to have ſailed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the preceeding <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To add to our Misfortune, I was at that time not able to take the Opportunity of a fair Wind, that then offer'd; becauſe I ſtaid for a great Convoy of Arms, and Proviſions, that were laden for me at <hi>Rochel,</hi> without which I could not proceed; I had continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it for three Months. In the midſt of theſe Perplexities, I underſtood they were, at laſt, arrived at <hi>Port Lewis;</hi> where they were forc'd to put in, to avoid a Squadron of the Enemy, that had for ſome time cruis'd upon that Coaſt, and had them in ſight. By this, I found our Naval Preparation upon the very point of miſcarrying; our Proviſions were already much diminiſh'd, and the Appearance very great, that the Enemy's Squadron would remain there, and we utterly conſume our Proviſions in the Road of <hi>Brest:</hi> Upon which I fix'd my Reſolution; which, altho' it ſeem'd very hazardous, was yet the only Method that the Poſture of my Affairs would permit me to take: It was, to find out my Convoy, and even to diſengage them at the hazard of a Battle: Now, altho' I ſhould have the beſt of it, yet it could not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a mighty Inconveniency to me: But I flatter'd my ſelf, that poſſibly I might not be diſcover'd by the Enemy; or, in caſe of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103058:11"/>
with them, get indifferently well off, and refit at <hi>Port Lewis;</hi> and then try to get out; and happen what would, by whatſoever way it ſhould be my Fate to be loſt, I had rather have been ruin'd with our Arms in our Hands, than miſcarry for want of Reſolution, and in a ſhameful Abode there.</p>
            <p>Accordingly I had given my Orders to ſail the next Day; at which time I underſtood by Signals from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhant,</hi> that they deſcried a very large Fleet. We knew very well, by ſeveral Accounts, that there were about Forty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War abroad, with Orders to cruize before <hi>Brest,</hi> and by all manner of means to prevent my paſſage; by which my Departure ſeem'd impoſſible, my Enterprize defeated, and my Misfortune unavoidable. However, I propos'd other Matters to my ſelf, and ſtuck to my firſt Reſolution, not thinking my Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion much worſe for this News; the little way between <hi>Brest</hi> and <hi>Port Lewis,</hi> or the entrance into the River of <hi>Morbian,</hi> of which I had taken particular Care to inform my ſelf, that I might ſecure my Retreat into it, gave me ſome Hopes to believe, that I might probably get in thither, before I ſhould be too deeply engag'd in a Battle; and then having once got on Board what the Convoy had brought me, I might, by the Favour of the long Nights, get away, without being ſeen by the Enemy; or, at the worſt, eſcape with ſmall damage, in a running Fight. So this great Fleet did no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103058:12"/>
more alter my Circumſtances, than if it had been a ſmall Squadron; againſt which, in the Juncture I was in, the hazard of fighting was as dangerous as with a Capital Fleet, my Care being to get away, and proſecute the Buſineſs of my Project. Beſides, if I could get a little before the Enemies, there was no great appearance for them either to come eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly up with me, or that they could be in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to purſue me for Two thouſand Leagues that I might lead them: I had, moreover, the opportunity of ſeparating my Ships in the Night, by ordering them different Courſes to the appointed Rendezvous.</p>
            <p>The Governor of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhant</hi> ſent an Expreſs to aſſure me, That he could diſcern Forty Men of War, amongſt which were Five <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or <hi>Dutch</hi> Flags: I received this News at Midnight, and making uſe of it in a manner quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Opinions of them that ſent it me, I made the ſailing Signal, and was under Sail by that time it was Day, it being upon the Seventh of <hi>January,</hi> 1697. I had, ſome Days before, ſent my Orders to the Veſſels at <hi>Port Lewis,</hi> to come away immediately, running all Hazards, to join me; but to keep ſo near the Shoar, that the Enemies Ships might not dare to approach them, or to avoid their Cannon by running into the Ports that are upon that Coaſt; which are good enough to cover ſuch ſmall Veſſels, as I expected, from the Danger of Cruiſers. I had ſent the <hi>Mutine</hi>-Frigat, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103058:12"/>
the <hi>Providence</hi>-Brigantine, to Convoy them, who expected them at <hi>Pennemarc</hi>-Point.</p>
            <p>We were hardly got out of the <hi>Goulet</hi> when we ſaw the Fleet appear at <hi>Point Raz,</hi> with the ſmall Convoy I had ſent to them; whereupon I came immediately to an Anchor at <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theaume,</hi> where I made all the haſte I could to get our Proviſions on Board our Ships and Fly-boats, and by extraordinary Diligence, I was in a Condition of Sailing the next Day.</p>
            <p>We had hardly got into our Courſe, when the <hi>Scepter</hi> ſtruck upon a place, where, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of Navigation, there could be no manner of danger, after having ſtruck three times very violently, we thought ſhe was juſt upon ſinking, eſpecially when we ſaw a great many Planks floating upon the Water; at the ſame time we perceiv'd her to float, and running immediately to the Pumps, we found ſhe did not make one drop of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: We could not tell what to think of this Accident; however, it was concluded, that it could not be a Rock ſhe had ſtruck upon, but upon ſome ſunk Veſſel that floated under Water, which being leſs ſtrong than the <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter,</hi> had occaſioned us that Alarm by the breaking of her Planks, without any ways prejudicing the <hi>Scepter.</hi> We continu'd our Courſe, endeavouring to avoid the Enemies: I had ſo regulated my ſelf to the Tides, as to be, by the beginning of the Night, at <hi>Pennemarc</hi>-Point;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103058:13"/>
beſides, there was no great probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I ſhould be diſcover'd in ſailing ſo little a way, eſpecially by reaſon of our holding ſo near to the Coaſt. I reſolv'd at the ſame time to ſteer directly from <hi>Pennemarc,</hi> to the Coaſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> which I deſign'd to leave to the <hi>Southward.</hi> This Courſe, ſo contrary to what is cuſtomarily taken, to get clear of the Land, which the Enemies muſt know I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd; and upon which, moſt probably, they form'd their Method of Cruiſing, was the moſt likelieſt Expedient to deceive them. This had the deſired Effect, and the Wind continuing favourable, I firſt made Cape <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegal,</hi> and afterwards continued my Courſe towards the Iſland of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> where I arriv'd in Fifty five Days; during which there happen'd nothing remarkable, unleſs it was, that after having paſs'd the Tropick, we met with <hi>West South-West</hi> Winds, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary, which is not uſual.</p>
            <p>The pleaſure of arriving at Cape <hi>Francis,</hi> which was that part of S. <hi>Domingo</hi> that I came to, was mitigated by ſeveral Accidents. I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood there, that Capt. <hi>Deſaugets,</hi> who commanded Three Ships in thoſe Seas, for whom I had Orders to join himſelf with my Squadron, was Eight Days before my Arrival ſail'd upon his Return to <hi>France.</hi> I was there likewiſe inform'd by Monſ. <hi>Daunou,</hi> Lieutenant-Governour of the Iſland, that the Succours which Monſ. <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103058:13"/>
of the Coaſt had prepar'd for me, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in about Four hundred Men, altho' he had Orders to join me with the Strength of the whole Colony.</p>
            <p>It is true, that by good Fortune all the Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of thoſe parts, which are uſually called <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> were met together at that time: It was thought that I might find a Party of them; but it was no ways to be imagin'd, that I ſhould find them all; for they go out and come in as they pleaſe; conſequently, this Aſſiſtance could not be computed at 14 or 1500 Men, as I was made to believe I ſhould find at St. <hi>Domingo;</hi> neither did they exceed 600: So I was near upon a Thouſand Men behind of my Account.</p>
            <p>The Departure of Capt. <hi>Deſaugets,</hi> depriv'd me of a like Number of Men, and two great Ships. Moreover, I was fallen ſhort of two great Ships, and ſeveral Frigats, ſpecified in my firſt Project, by which means I found my ſelf reduc'd to half the Force I propos'd at the beginning.</p>
            <p>I did not think fit to come to an Anchor at the Cape, but left there Three Frigates, the <hi>Mutine,</hi> the <hi>Avenant,</hi> and the <hi>Marin,</hi> to take in ſuch Forces as might be drawn from thence, and the freſh Proviſions which Commiſſary <hi>Du Tilleul</hi> was to ſupply my Squadron with.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103058:14"/>S. <hi>Vandrille,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Marin,</hi> that was ſent two Months before I left <hi>France,</hi> with Orders for Monſ. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> to have the Forces ready that were appointed for my aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, after he had carried his Diſpatches to <hi>Petit Guaves,</hi> ſailed for the Cape, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me there.</p>
            <p>In his paſſage from <hi>France</hi> to St. <hi>Domin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> he was attack'd by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship of 54 Guns, who notwithſtanding her Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, was forc'd to retire with Shame, after a Fight of ſeveral Hours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſaugets</hi> going for the <hi>Hondura's,</hi> before he return'd to <hi>France,</hi> had order'd the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>De la Motte d'Heran,</hi> on Board the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> taken from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to ſail directly for <hi>France,</hi> with the <hi>Favorite</hi>-Frigat, whom I found at the Cape upon his departure. Theſe two Ships were both mann'd with the <hi>Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi>'s Crew only, conſequently very weak Men of War; wherefore I reſolv'd to make uſe of but one of them, to put all the Men into her, and leave the other Ship at <hi>Petit Guaves.</hi> By Virtue of the King's Letter, which I had to <hi>Deſaugets,</hi> and his Squadron, I order'd <hi>La Motte d'Heran,</hi> to join me; which he did, and choſe the <hi>Chriſt</hi> that he commanded.</p>
            <p>About Eight a Clock, upon the Sixth of <hi>March,</hi> I came to an Anchor over-againſt <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> the uſual Reſidence of Monſ. <hi>Du Caſſe;</hi> who came immediately on Board, to adviſe with me about the ſhipping of the Men he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103058:14"/>
was to bring me; and ſeeing that I did not diſſemble neither my ſurprize, nor my trouble, at the ſmall Number of Men he had provided for me, he proteſted, that he had done all he could; and continually endeavoured to make me have a great Opinion of the good Succeſs of this Attempt; for, that the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were at that Juncture all together, and would every Man of 'em perform Wonders. We agreed that he ſhould go to <hi>Petit Guaves,</hi> and that I would be ready by that time it was Day, to get into the Port: <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> came thither to join me, having a Deſign on foot which I did not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine; I brought him the Duplicate of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which he had received from St. <hi>Vandrille,</hi> which he did not read when I delivered it to him, by reaſon it was wrote in Cyphers. There was added in that Letter, without my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he was to contrive the Means of ſucceeding in an Attempt that was approv'd by His Majeſty, without damaging the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: This Reſtriction did in ſome meaſure deprive me of the Power of commanding his Forces, ſeeing he had an opportunity of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to keep them for the preſervation of his Colony. He ſaid, That he would not inſiſt upon Terms with me, as being perſwaded that I would have a regard to his Character. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, That the greateſt Character he could pretend to, was that of being Captain of a Ship, which he had the Honour to command by his Commiſſion; all that I could do, was,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103058:15"/>
that he ſhould ſerve in that Capacity, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Seniority, which did ſubmit him to ſeveral others, who, nevertheleſs, would not pretend to concern themſelves with the Forces of his Government; in relation to whom, I ſhould addreſs my ſelf to him, that he was to accept this Propoſition, or not to embark with me, for I had no Orders to compel him.</p>
            <p>After refuſing theſe Offers he left me; and thinking no more of him, I was ſurpriz'd to hear, that he took all imaginable Care for what was perſonally neceſſary to him in this Expedition; and that he reported, He would rather come on Board as a private Soldier, than not engage in ſo glorious an Affair. He ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much Courage and Deſire of Glory in his Diſcourſe, and it is pity, that he afterwards diſcover'd his Reſolution to proceed from Motives, and Intereſts, ſomething leſs gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
            <p>In the mean time we employ'd our ſelves in getting of Water, Wood, and other things neceſſary for the Squadron; and to fit up the Veſſels of the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> which were all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigg'd; without the help of the Rigging and Cordage, that I ordered to be delivered them by my Squadron, it would have been impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to put to Sea; we likewiſe diſtributed the Proviſions there, which I had brought for the Forces that were to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark with me; in ſhort, we prepared all things for our Departure. It was then neceſſary to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103058:15"/>
regulate the Pretenſions of the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> who deſir'd to be aſſur'd of their Shares of the expected Prizes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Free-booters, are, for the moſt part, compos'd of thoſe that deſert from Ships that come upon the Coaſt: The Advantage they bring to the Governours, protects them againſt the Proſecutions of the Law; beſides, all thoſe that are apprehended in <hi>France,</hi> as Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabonds, or ſuch as can give no Account of themſelves, are ſent to theſe Iſlands, where they are oblig'd to ſerve for Three Years. The firſt that gets them, obliges them to work in the Plantations; at the end of the Term of Servitude, ſome Body lends them a Gun, and to Sea they go a <hi>Buccaniering.</hi> This Profeſſion hath maintain'd it ſelf a long while by this ſort of Recruits, and ſubſiſt by their Pyracies; they were formerly altogether independent, but of late Years, they have been reduc'd under the Government of the Coaſt of S. <hi>Domingo;</hi> they have Commiſſions given them for which they pay the Tenth of all their Prizes, and are now call'd the King's Subjects: For the Governors of St. <hi>Domingo</hi> being enrich'd by them, do mightily extol them for the Damages they do to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and endeavour to have it believed, that the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> are the ſtrength and ſupport of the Colony; whereas, they are, in effect the Ruine of it: For if ſuch as are convey'd thither, were kept from the Liberty of embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing this infamous Profeſſion, which an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103058:16"/>
for all ſorts of Crimes renders ſo much belov'd, we ſhould not have loſt, in a few Years, above Six thouſand Men, that might have improv'd and peopl'd the Colony. And thus, indeed, they would have been truly the ſtrength and ſupport of the place.</p>
            <p>As to other Matters, altho' they are pleas'd to be counted the King's Subjects, yet it is with ſo much Arrogance, as obliges all thoſe that are deſirous to make uſe of them, to court them in the moſt flattering Terms. This not being agreeable to my Diſpoſition, and being they were in the Dominions of His Maieſty, and eſteeming them as His Subjects, which the Governor was oblig'd to deliver to me; I plainly told them, That they ſhould find me a Commander to lead them on, but not as a Companion of their Fortune; that if they made any Difficulties, either to embark or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, I would certainly burn all their Veſſels, even to the pooreſt Boats, and inevitably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of the Means for ſome Years, if not for ever, of continuing their Depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>It was fear'd, that upon theſe Threats they would betake themſelves to the Woods, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their uſual Retreat upon any Diſſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But I knew they apprehended very much the Execution of my Menaces; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that the Governor, who is ſo highly concern'd in their Pyracies, would omit no ſort of Care to retain them in their Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:103058:16"/>The Demand they made, of having their Share, in the Diviſion of the Prizes, ſecur'd to them, was very reaſonable; therefore I explain'd my ſelf in Writing, and caus'd it to be fix'd up in ſeveral places, implying, <hi>That they ſhould, Man for Man, have the ſame Shares of Booty, that was allowed to the Men on Board the King's Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was informed of their Cuſtoms, and that of divers ways of dividing the Shares, (which is commonly a very troubleſome Buſineſs); the moſt uſual Method was this, of reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Number of the Men; for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: A Veſſel of a Hundred Men, hath dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Allowance that is made to another of but Fifty, ſo the reſt in proportion. I made no manner of delay in the Choice I was to make; as likewiſe, to acquaint them, that I could not meddle with any thing that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to the King, the Admiral, and the Undertakers of the Armament. That His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had been pleaſed to allow to the ſeveral Ships Companies, the Tenth of the Firſt Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and a Thirtieth part of all the others: And I engag'd my ſelf in Writing, to give the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> the ſame Terms. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> told me, that I had taken the eaſieſt Method, deſiring me only to leave with him the Original of that Writing, including the Frigat <hi>Pontchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>train,</hi> commanded by Lieutenant <hi>Mornay,</hi> who deſired to ſerve in the Squadron upon the ſame Conditions that I had granted to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103058:17"/>
               <hi>Buccaniers:</hi> There was likewiſe comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, at the Deſires of <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> a Frigat of S. <hi>Malo,</hi> fitted both for War and Traffick. We ſhall have occaſion to mention this Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting again, in the Sequel of our Story.</p>
            <p>Upon the Eighteenth, all the Ships that I had left at Cape <hi>Francis,</hi> having join'd my Squadron with <hi>La Motte d'Heran,</hi> whom I had likewiſe ordered to join me; I made ready on the Nineteenth to go and Anchor at Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> being the furtheſt Weſtern Point of S. <hi>Domingo;</hi> the Water there is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and eaſier to be got, than in any other place, ſo it was abſolutely neceſſary for me to touch there; beſides, I was very deſirous to get out of Port, to oblige the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> to come on Board, which they ever defer to the laſt moment; however they at laſt got on Board, ſeeing me at ſome diſtance, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the Squadron, as alſo the <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> which <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> had choſen for himſelf; when, on a ſudden, a violent North-Wind, which is very extraordinary, and rarely known in this Seaſon, ſcatter'd not only the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> but likewiſe all the Ships of my Squadron, inſomuch that I continu'd alone for above Thirty Hours, two Chaloups ſent from the <hi>Scepter,</hi> to the aſſiſtance of two <hi>Buccaniers</hi> in danger of ſtranding, not being able to get up with me; but good Weather coming on, we all met upon the 28th, in the Road of <hi>Irois,</hi> three Leagues diſtant from Cape <hi>Tiburon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103058:17"/>Until then, I had kept my Deſign ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, not being wholly determin'd on the Matter: <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> who underſtood by his Letters from Court, that the principal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Expedition was upon <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena,</hi> did judge the execution impoſſible, by reaſon of the ſeveral Accidents already mention'd, and the ſmall number of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with me. He repreſented unto me, with much appearance of Reaſon, That, according to the laſt Advices from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Coaſts, the Galleons muſt be at <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> or upon their way to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> in order to their return for <hi>Spain;</hi> that we might reaſonably hope to meet with them, by ſteering that courſe; and that, by our ſtrength, we might reckon our ſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of them, altho' we found them in <hi>Porto Bello;</hi> for notwithſtanding the Port is defended by three Caſtles, yet it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enough for us to get in, and poſſeſs our ſelves of thoſe Caſtles, by means of our Bombs. But I had my Reaſons not to follow this Opinion: The Galleons might as well be at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> as at Sea, and I was ſenſible, by my own Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, how uncertain 'tis to meet Ships at Sea, a thing not to be depended upon; moreover, it ſeem'd plain to me, that the leſs the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were in a Condition to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103058:18"/>
defend themſelves at <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> the leſs Reaſon I had to hope for an Advantage by their Defeat, otherwiſe than in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour I might gain; for they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have burnt, or ſunk, their Ships, upon the approach of ſuch a Squadron as I had the Honour to Command, and that Treaſure not loſt to them, muſt have been abſolutely ſo to me, ſince I could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly have continued long enough there, to get it out of the Water.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations abſolutely diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me from going firſt of all to <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> which Voyage would have ſpent my Proviſions, and render'd me uncapable of any other conſiderable Attempt. <hi>Vera Cruz</hi> was a more likely place; for we were well aſſur'd, that one of the Flotas had been there ever ſince the beginning of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and that they could not go away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> therefore I could not miſs meeting with them; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, my Forces were ſufficient to make me Maſter of the City, which may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred without our being expoſed to the Fire of the Caſtle, which is impregnable by its advantageous ſituation: It is built on a Rock, in the middle of the Sea, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded on all ſides with extraordinary Fortifications. However, with my great
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103058:18"/>
ſtore of Artillery, I could, in a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, have reduc'd that Caſtle to Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; beſides the Bombs that I could have us'd from my Ships, I might have rais'd what Batteries of Cannon and Mortars I pleas'd on Shoar, which is not above 200 Yards from it.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not have run the Riſque here, as I muſt have done at <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Spaniards</hi> burn their Ships, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of the Silver: For it being well known, that they do embark the Plate there, but a very few Days before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the Flota, conſequently, at the worſt, I could only have loſt the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes, of which I made little account. In ſhort, 'tis probable, I ſhould have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in this Expedition, had I not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome Advices at St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned me new Perplexities, <hi>viz.</hi> that tho' the Plate was not us'd to be embark'd until the Day before the Fleet ſail'd, and was brought from <hi>Mexico</hi> to <hi>Vera Cruz,</hi> long before 'twas put on Board; yet, of late Years, upon ſome Jealouſies, they bring it no farther than <hi>Pueblo de los An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos,</hi> forty Leagues up the Country, from whence 'tis convey'd directly on Board the Galleons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103058:19"/>According to the Rules of Navigation, which 'tis not neceſſary to inſert here, the Galleons could not ſail until the Month of <hi>May,</hi> yet they might come away later, even until the Month of <hi>August;</hi> ſo if they had not by chance taken the reſolution of coming away with the firſt of the Seaſon, it being then but <hi>March,</hi> and we not above three Weeks ſail from them, I did foreſee that our Deſign would be ruin'd by my arrival before the Plate was brought down, and I was no ways in a condition of march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forty Leagues, with ſuch a ſmall Body of Forces, in an Enemy's, and well-inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited Country. Moreover, I was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to begin with a place, that would have fruſtrated my farther Intentions, in caſe I had been unſucceſsful: For ſuch is the Nature of the Gulf of <hi>Mexico,</hi> at the bottom whereof <hi>Vera Cruz</hi> is ſituated, that at our coming out again, it would not be poſſible for us to entertain any other Thoughts, but thoſe of returning to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> as well becauſe of the length of the Voyage, as becauſe the Winds and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Currents, would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented all other Attempts to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:103058:19"/>The only place I could fix my Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions upon, was <hi>Carthagena,</hi> which lay to Windward; and altho' I ſhould have miſs'd of my Aim there, yet it would not have been any Obſtacle to my other Deſigns, not even againſt <hi>Vera Cruz,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I conſum'd my time by adventurouſly falling upon the firſt place, without a well-grounded aſſurance of carrying it: The ſmall number of my Forces, was the only thing that could diſſwade me from this Attempt: But this want of Strength, might be remedied by good Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Capt. <hi>Venner,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> having been ſeveral Years in the Service of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> and Commanded ſeveral of their Ships, was lately come into the Service of <hi>France,</hi> and was plac'd on Board <hi>Deſaugets,</hi> until ſome other Employ ſhould be given him. This Officer was very well acquainted with the Coaſts and Places of the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> he had likewiſe ſome knowledge of Geometry, and by the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Canette,</hi> my principal Ingenier, I got him to draw ſeveral Plans, eſpecially that of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> which we found to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103058:20"/>
as exact as any thing could be expected that was made by Memory.</p>
            <p>My firſt Deſign was to have immediately landed with Five thouſand Men, near <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena,</hi> not including the Seamen: I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have drawn theſe Forces from the places before-mentioned, with which I reckoned I ſhould be able to force the place, tho' beſides its ordinary defence, the whole ſtrength of the Galleons ſhould have been in it. But I was all manner of ways very much miſtaken in my Account, ſcarce ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one half of the Forces I propos'd, with which there was no probability of taking a place ſo famous in <hi>India,</hi> and ſo well known in <hi>Europe,</hi> for its Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which I found to be even better than they were reputed to be. The Ships were to Anchor in the open Sea, and by that means muſt have been expos'd to all the Inconveniences of the bad Seaſon, which was not quite over; beſides, I might have been ſurpriz'd by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Squadron, which I knew had Orders to follow me. In this caſe there was no likelihood for me to expect any Service from the Sea-men, it being altogether ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to leave them on Board to work the Ships in bad Weather; but then agen, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103058:20"/>
only the Land-Forces to re-embark, I might, upon any occaſion, ſoon put my ſelf into a poſture of defence.</p>
            <p>Then I imagin'd, that if inſtead of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking <hi>Carthagena,</hi> I only attempted <hi>Boc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cachica,</hi> which defends the entrance into that vaſt Harbour, called the <hi>Lagune</hi> of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and ſhould carry that Fort, the reſt would be eaſily acquired, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I might bring my Ships under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of this Fort, and thereby make uſe of the Sea-men that might be then ſpar'd from the Ships, which would in ſome meaſure make up the want of Land-Forces.</p>
            <p>However, this Deſign had its Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties likewiſe: For the paſſage which this Fort defends, is ſo narrow, and winding, that there's no ſailing through it, but you muſt warp your Ships along by their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors and Cables; now two Ships riding within, can prevent this work, and alone defend the entrance againſt the ſtrongeſt Fleet: I could not imagine, but that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would uſe that Precaution, in caſe the Galleons had been at <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103058:21"/>On the other hand, if I could make a Deſcent on any other part of the Iſland, at one end of which ſtands <hi>Carthagena,</hi> at the other <hi>Boccachica,</hi> I might probably ſurmount all Difficulties, by expeditiouſly landing of my Cannon; with which croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Iſland, and raiſing of Batteries on the Banks of the <hi>Tagon,</hi> I knew very well, I could either ſink, or force away any Ships that ſhould be poſted to defend the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance: As to the Fort, I did no ways doubt the taking of it with the help of my Bombs, in ſpight of any Succours the Enemy might bring to it by Land.</p>
            <p>Being once in poſſeſſion of <hi>Boccachica,</hi> I had ſeveral Reaſons for good hopes, in caſe the Galleons were not there, that I ſhould, by the help of the Sea-men (which I might take when the Ships were ſecur'd) be enabled to attempt <hi>Carthagena;</hi> and if the Galleons were there, then I purpos'd to attack them; and in caſe they ſhould reſolve to ſink themſelves, then I ſhould be able ſo to terrifie the place with my Bombs, that they would yield to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, that might re-imburſe my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers; and from thence I could after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſteer to ſome other Leeward place.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:103058:21"/>After I had duly weigh'd theſe Matters, I abſolutely reſolv'd upon ſailing to <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena,</hi> and I publiſh'd my Reſolution; which was applauded and received with all the ſigns of Satisfaction from the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> propos'd the ſending away two Frigats of <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> to precede me, which ſhould land in the Night near <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena,</hi> to take what Priſoners they could make, and carry them to <hi>Sambee,</hi> twelve Leagues to Windward of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and there expect our coming. Capt. <hi>Pierre,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Blou,</hi> were inſtantly commanded to ſail upon this Deſign; but inſtead of executing theſe Orders, the deſire of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging, according to their uſual Cuſtom, engag'd them to chaſe ſome ſmall Veſſels they met, which they had not the Courage to board, after they had driven them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground; and this occaſioned them to loſe ſo much time, that without having been at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> they arrived after me at <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee,</hi> where a ſudden Guſt from the North-Eaſt, called here a Breeze, had forc'd me to come to an Anchor, and wait for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Weather to appear before <hi>Carthagena</hi> in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103058:22"/>On the Thirteenth, the Wind being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, we got under Sail, and directed our Courſe for <hi>Carthagena.</hi> The whole Fleet was compos'd of theſe Ships: Seven Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats from Eight to Twenty four Guns, on board them about Six hundred and fifty <hi>Buccaniers.</hi> One hundred and ten Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of S. <hi>Domingo,</hi> One hundred and ſeventy Garriſon Soldiers of the Coaſt, and One hundred and eighty Negroes; were diſpers'd on board the Men of War, and Flyboats belonging to the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron. This was all the aſſiſtance which I received from the Government of St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat were join'd to us as before mentioned, the one having Forty Guns, and One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men; the other Twenty four Guns, and Sixty Men.</p>
            <p>The Squadron was compos'd of Seven great Ships.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scepter</hi> carrying Eighty four Guns, and Six hundred and fifty Men, commanded by <hi>Guillotin:</hi> I was on board this Ship.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103058:22"/>The St. <hi>Lewis</hi> of Sixty four Guns, and Four hundred and twenty Men, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Levy,</hi> who acted as Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fort</hi> of Seventy Guns, and Four hundred and fifty Men, commanded by the Viſcount <hi>Coetlogon,</hi> who ſerv'd as Rear-Admiral.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Vermandois, Apollo, Furieux,</hi> and St. <hi>Michael,</hi> all four of Sixty Guns each, and Three hundred and fifty Men, were commanded by <hi>Dubuiſſon, Gombaud, La Motte Michel,</hi> and the Chevalier <hi>de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Christ,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi>-Prize, commanded by the Chevalier <hi>de la Motte d'Heran,</hi> of Two hundred and twenty Men, and Forty four Guns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Avenant,</hi> by the Chevalier <hi>Francine,</hi> Two hundred Men, and Thirty Guns.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Marin,</hi> commanded by St. <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drille,</hi> had One hundred and eighty Men, and Twenty eight Guns.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:103058:23"/>The <hi>Eclatant,</hi> Bomb-Veſſel, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>De Mons,</hi> had Sixty Men.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Providence</hi>-Brigantine, of Thirty Men, and Four Guns, commanded by the Chevalier <hi>De L'Eſcouet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Flyboats.</p>
            <p>Four Boats, call'd by the French <hi>Traverſier,</hi> who had each of them one Gun, and a Mortar.</p>
            <p>On board theſe Ships, and Veſſels, were One hundred and ten Officers, Fifty five Guards Marine, Two thouſand one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Sea-men, One thouſand ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Soldiers, effective Men.</p>
            <p>Before I left the Road of <hi>Irois,</hi> or Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> which is the ſame place, I had regulated the Deſcent, and the Manner of employing our Forces.</p>
            <p>The Captains of the Men of War, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe that effectually were ſo, (but not all thoſe who commanded for ſuch, as did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Galliot-Captains, and ſome Men of War Lieutenants) were to ſerve as General-Officers, dividing themſelves according to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103058:23"/>
their Seniority, to be alternately aſhoar and on board; for it was abſolutely neceſſary to have ſome of them always in Command on board the Ships. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> had the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of all the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> and Inhabitants of the Coaſt, whom I left to him, under their ancient Captains.</p>
            <p>By Order of the Court, there was a State Major, compos'd of <hi>Sorel,</hi> Inſpector-General of the Marine Troops of <hi>Brittany.</hi> The deſire of ſerving in this Expedition, induc'd him likewiſe to take upon him the Function of Major-General, but taking place only as Captain: of <hi>Theſut,</hi> Major: of two Aid-Majors-General, who were the Chevaliers <hi>Jaucour,</hi> and <hi>De Pointis:</hi> a Sub-Major-General <hi>Beraudin;</hi> and ſome Guards Marine, as Sub-Majors:</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Du Tilleul,</hi> Commiſſary.</p>
            <p>One principal Ingenier, and another, <hi>viz. Canette</hi> and <hi>Tangey,</hi> for whom were compos'd two Brigades of Officers, or Guards-Marine, as alſo ſome Voluntier-Soldiers, that were in ſome meaſure thought capable of ſerving as Ingeniers. The Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Ferriere, du Crest,</hi> and <hi>Courſy,</hi> were the chief of theſe Brigades; the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers <hi>de Neſmond,</hi> and <hi>Pouillermont,</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:103058:24"/>
               <hi>La Lande, du Ches,</hi> and <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> Guards-Marine, choſe to ſerve as Aids de Camps under me.</p>
            <p>Six Battalions were compos'd of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers on board the King's Ships; the firſt was a Body of Two hundred and fifty Grenadiers, drawn out of all the reſt, commanded by <hi>La Roche de Vigier,</hi> Captain of a Frigat, but then ſerving as ſecond Captain on board the <hi>Scepter,</hi> commanded, I ſay, by him, as Collonel, <hi>le Chevalier de Vezins,</hi> Lieutenant of a Man of War, as Lieutenant-Collonel; <hi>Vaujoux</hi> ſerv'd as Major, St. <hi>Lazare d' Ayde, Framine, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſier,</hi> and <hi>Vignancourt,</hi> had the Command of the Five Companies that made this Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</p>
            <p>The Five Senior Lieutenants of Infantry Marine, commanded as Collonels in the Five other Battalions of Three hundred Men each; who were the Chevalier <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles, le Chenau, de Breſme, Simonet;</hi> the Guards-Marine were divided among them to augment the number of Officers. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, I made Detachments of Four hundred Seamen, under their own Officers, all arm'd with Scythes and Piſtols; upon occaſion, theſe were to be commanded by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103058:24"/>
Lieutenants of Ships, that had no Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, who were <hi>de Vaulx, Longuejoue, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavy, Siglas,</hi> and <hi>Sabran,</hi> theſe were to be reliev'd by Five Captains of Fireſhips that were on board our Squadron.</p>
            <p>The One hundred and ſeventy Soldiers drawn out of the Garriſons on the Coaſt of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> were in a ſeparate Body, and commanded by <hi>Beaumont.</hi> The One hundred and ten Inhabitants, and the One hundred and eighty Negroes, made each of them another. The <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were all in one Troop.</p>
            <p>The Plans, and Memoirs, which I had of ſeveral places, of whoſe Errors I have much reaſon to complain, were neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs true in one point: For they gave me a plain aſſurance, that if we did not ſeize at our arrival at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> upon a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Eminence, and a Church called <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe,</hi> that commands the Avenues, all the Treaſure would be carried off, the greateſt part being in Gold and Emeraulds, eaſily to be tranſported up into the Country; which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would not fail to do, upon the approach of ſuch a formidable Fleet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103058:25"/>To get poſſeſſion of this Poſt, I reſolv'd to land the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> the Night after my coming to an Anchor, they being very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for ſuch an Attempt, as being accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to marching and ſubſiſting in the Woods, where each of them carries his own Proviſions, and lives upon what he kills; ſo I was inform'd at leaſt: Thus, not being encumber'd with any Baggage, their March might be kept ſecret, their Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption unexpected, and, in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, their Retreat ſecure, by ways un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable to others. I had concerted with <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> all things relating to this Deſign, which he undertook to ſee executed: We agreed upon the Signals he ſhould make me by Fires from the Hills, to acquaint me whether he wanted any aſſiſtance, or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to re-imbark his Men; or upon taking of the Poſt, whether he was in a Condition of maintaining it, or not. On my part, I was to inform him by Signals from the Ships, of my Condition, and the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which various Accidents might oblige me to take.</p>
            <p>Having concluded upon this Method of executing our Deſign, we arriv'd between <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and Point <hi>Hicacos,</hi> four Leagues
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103058:25"/>
to the Eaſtward, where finding good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorage in a great Bay, which the Land makes by running out to the Southward, we came to an Anchor about Four a Clock, two Leagues from the City, on the ſame Day, being the Thirteenth. The Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron was got ready in the Morning at <hi>Sambee,</hi> and I delivered all my Orders by Signals: By this diligence I was ſure to make a ſecure Deſcent, it not being poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that an Enemy could be able to guard all the Shoar, or march down time enough to hinder our landing.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Ships were come to an Anchor, I made the Signal for the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loups, (that were to land the <hi>Buccaniers)</hi> to go on board their Frigats, ſo ſoon as it was dark; and to them to be in a readineſs for the Boats, altho' it was reſolved they ſhould not embark until Midnight, to the end they might be aſhoar ſome Hours only before Day-light.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the <hi>Fort,</hi> the <hi>Mutine,</hi> and the Bomb-Veſſel, according to their Orders, were advanc'd towards the City; the laſt near enough to bombard, and the other two to guard her. I expected, by thus employing of the Enemy with my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:103058:26"/>
Bombs, to divert them from taking other neceſſary Precautions.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd, in order to their landing, they did not behave themſelves ſo heroically as <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> had boaſted of them: For this ſeparation from the King's Forces, afforded them a proſpect of the dreadfulleſt Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; they began to apprehend the want of Proviſions in the Woods, where they were us'd to ſubſiſt many Days, when they were only to rob and cut Peoples Throats ſleeping, whereas now they were to march againſt a People that ſtood on their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; yet to take away one of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that covered their fear, we deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them Proviſion, and the Major-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, after much ſtirring, got them at laſt into the Boats.</p>
            <p>All was in a readineſs for the Deſcent, when I fortunately reſolv'd to viſit the Shoar; for the moſt proper place of landing: One would not have thought, that in a great Bay, ſhelter'd from the Winds that uſually Reign upon this Coaſt, where Ships find a good Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and the Sea calm, it ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to get aſhoar; but ſcarce were
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103058:26"/>
we come to it, when the Waves breaking upon the Rocks even with the Water, did but little miſs of filling my Canoa quite full of Water at once: <hi>Levy, Du Caſſe,</hi> and <hi>Tilleul,</hi> were with me. We rowed down the Strand towards <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena,</hi> in hopes of finding ſome proper place; but there the Sea ran higher than it did from whence we came; and when we were fall'n ſo low, that it was not poſſible to proceed farther without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging our ſelves among ſeveral little Lakes that from this part water all the Territory of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> our Canoe came a-thwart a Sea, that filled her half full of Water; and now, in all probability, our Enterprize, as yet not begun, was like to end in a Goal: But <hi>Levy</hi> leaping into the Water, and by his Example en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Sea-men, that followed him, to uſe their utmoſt Efforts, we at length got our Canoa a-float, that had ſtruck on the Rock, and deliver'd our ſelves from that imminent Danger. Our firſt Care was, by the other Canoas of the Majors, to diſpatch Orders to the Chaloups, not to come near the Shoar; where, embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs'd by the great number of People on board them, and being every way larger, drawing more Water, and not ſo well
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103058:27"/>
provided with Rowers, as my Canoa was, their Ruine muſt have been inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>We were then, notwithſtanding all our Draughts and Memoirs, oblig'd to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that <hi>Carthagena</hi> was inacceſſible on this ſide: For if in ſo calm a Day, the Sea was ſo boiſterous as we found it, what were we to expect in other Weather? In ſhort, the ſtay we made in this Country, hath ſhewn us by Experience, as well as inform'd us by the Relations of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, that the Sea upon all this Coaſt, and in all Seaſons, is a natural and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Rampart; and that <hi>Carthagena</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable only by the Lake, which makes the Harbour.</p>
            <p>I reflected with Concern on this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous Adventure; I foreſaw, that in not being able to poſſeſs my ſelf of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Poſt of <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe,</hi> I ſhould afford the <hi>Spaniards</hi> an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſeveral Days to carry off whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were deſirous to ſave, by reaſon I could not be able to come at them, until I had taken the Fort of <hi>Boccachica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:103058:27"/>Being wholly bent upon <hi>Boccachica,</hi> the Fleet got into a readineſs of ſailing in the Morning on the Fourteenth. We deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to paſs ſo nigh the Walls of <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena,</hi> as to do them all the miſchief my Guns could afford them; but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my utmoſt care to provide all things neceſſary for every Veſſel of the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> who have the Reputation of knowing this Coaſt, we found them ſo very ignorant, and ſo much at a loſs, that we durſt not attempt any thing upon the ſmall Informations that we could get from them; ſo we reſolv'd to take the ſureſt Precautions poſſible, by ordering the Chaloups to ſound before us. The <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter</hi> not finding Water enough, could not come within Shot of the Town; the <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the <hi>Fort,</hi> that drew leſs, even touch'd in ſeveral places. However, that did not hinder them from firing, until I made them a Signal to join the Fleet. The Enemy made no great Fire; yet we perceiv'd they had great Pieces, and good ſtore of them: To our admiration, we obſerv'd, that <hi>Carthagena</hi> was inclos'd only on this ſide with Palliſades, and old Walls that were in many places fall'n down; whereupon we founded our Projects and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103058:28"/>
Hopes of a lucky Event; not knowing that Nature had ſufficiently provided for the Security of this part, by the great Violence of the Sea that waſhes it: I touch'd twice, and came not this Night to an Anchor before <hi>Boccachica,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous firſt to inform my ſelf of all the Soundings; but came to an Anchor ſo ſoon as we found a proper depth. We underſtood afterwards, that the place we had been in all Day, was about eight Years ſince a Plain, where the People of <hi>Carthagena</hi> us'd to walk.</p>
            <p>I ſent away all the Chaloups, to ſound the Coaſt, even up to the Fort. I order'd St. <hi>Vandrille,</hi> on board the <hi>Marine,</hi> to an Anchor over-againſt the entrance, that ſo he might prevent any Boats from carrying of Advice, or Silver, to <hi>Porto Bello.</hi> All the Officers and Pilots, that had been out to ſound, aſſur'd me, that there was every where Water enough, even to Twenty Fathom, and near the Shoar; and the Coaſt jetting out to the Southward, had form'd near the Fort, a ſort of a Haven ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from the Violences of the Sea, which ran too high every-where elſe for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, and a ſmall neck of Land, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montory, did likewiſe protect us from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103058:28"/>
the Fire of the Fort; whereupon it was reſolv'd to come to an Anchor there, by Break of Day, next Morning, being the Fifteenth, and to take our Anchoring Births, according to the Diſpoſition of the place.</p>
            <p>All the Fleet were at Anchor on the Fifteenth at Noon: I immediately di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch'd away Major <hi>Theſut,</hi> to obſerve what part of the Shoar was moſt proper for a Deſcent. Upon his return I made the Signal for landing, and order'd <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> to take eighty Negroes, that were on board the <hi>Furieux,</hi> to embark with them on board the <hi>Pereagoes,</hi> which are a very light Veſſel, and therefore are in no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſtranding; with theſe I order'd him to make up towards <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and to come very near the Shoar, in two or three places, without endeavouring to land, but only to draw out the Enemies, if there were any, and by that means oblige them to diſcover what they were; and if there was no appearance of any, he was to inform me of it by a Signal: The Woods lie cloſe to the Sea-ſhoar, where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> might have kept themſelves conceal'd, and diſcharg'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us without appearing, which oblig'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103058:29"/>
me to this precaution; but <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſuch matter, landed with his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes, and hoiſted the white Flag upon a Rock. This acquainted me that he was landed: The Chaloups immediately made to ſhoar, and the Deſcent was made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any oppoſition. The Negroes were forthwith employed with their Bills and Hatchets, to make a way through the Wood to the Lake, on the other ſide of the Iſland, where we deſign'd to encamp, and make our Approaches to the Fort, the Ground on this ſide, towards the open Sea, not being ſo proper; beſides, it was neceſſary to cut off their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with <hi>Carthagena</hi> by Land. The Iſland, which is but narrow at the Point where the Fort is ſituated, is but a good quarter of a League from the Sea to the Lake, at the place our Negroes were cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, within half Cannon-ſhot of the Fort, from which we were covered by the Woods: The Way was made in a very little time, ſo that all our Troops were ranged quite croſs the Iſland, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king places of Arms in the ſeveral Paths of the Wood that lead to <hi>Carthagena;</hi> by this means we were ſoon poſted, and the Places of Arms, or <hi>Corps de Garde,</hi> were near enough to ſpeak to each other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:103058:29"/>While we were thus ſettling our ſelves a-ſhoar, the <hi>Lewis</hi> made a little more out, and began to Cannonade the Fort; ſometime afterwards, the <hi>Fort</hi> Man of War doing the ſame, as likewiſe the <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter,</hi> that follow'd at a little diſtance, the Battery began to be very warm, the Bomb-Galliot, and the <hi>Traverſier</hi> with one Mortar, having taken their Stations, played their parts very well, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued until Night. The Enemy only made a very ſlow Fire, which did not occaſion us much damage, only our Yards and Rigging ſuffer'd a little, and three Men were kill'd or wounded.</p>
            <p>In our approach to the Lake, we had a little crook'd the Way leading towards the Fort, to the end we might fall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly in with a little Plain, which (the People of St. <hi>Domingo</hi> brought hither for our Guides, told us) lay between the Lake, the Wood, and the Fort; ſo we came out at the foot of a riſing Ground, that was high and large enough to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, and from whence we had the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of examining the Fort, which is not above Muſquet-ſhot from it: We lodg'd our ſelves here, expecting the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:103058:30"/>
of Night, to examine the Ditch, and where it was proper, to open the Trenches, by cutting down a part of the Wood, which we perceiv'd to be much nearer to the Fort, than the Way we had cut: So ſoon as it was dark, the Major-General, and <hi>Canette,</hi> ſlipt away to make the Tour of the place, upon the Bank of the Ditch; which they did without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcover'd: <hi>Levy, Jaucourt,</hi> and I, being without deſign inſenſibly advanc'd into the Wood, until we perceiv'd our ſelves near to the Ditch, we were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to examine it. The obſcurity, and great ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſs of the Night, favour'd our Attempt; we met the Major-General and <hi>Canette</hi> who had been round; our Meeting happen'd to occaſion ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Noiſe, upon which the Sentinels fir'd, and we return'd, ſounding the Ground; which being proper for the Work, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd us in the Opinion of opening the Trench in that part of the Wood which I ſaid was neareſt to the Fort; beſides, a little Fen being between the Eminency and the Fort, did deprive us of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of carrying on our Work on that ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:103058:30"/>Upon the Sixteenth in the Morning, we began to make our Faſcines, Gabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to get our Artillery on Shoar, which we wanted, one of the Mortars being brought a-ſhoar in the Night, was ready to fire, and another was getting ready, when one of thoſe great <hi>Perea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes,</hi> that are much us'd in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and big enough to carry Sixty Men, came gently ſailing on to <hi>Boccachica,</hi> under the Shoar, which ſhe did not imagine to be in our poſſeſſion; but being perceiv'd by our Grenadiers there, they reſolutely took their opportunity, without waiting for Orders, and fir'd ſo thick into her, that at the firſt Diſcharge, they kill'd and wounded fifteen or ſixteen Men, ſeven or eight more being perfectly ſcar'd, leap'd into the Water, and were drown'd, the reſt throwing themſelves into the bottom of the <hi>Pereagoe;</hi> ſhe lay floating on the Water, until ſome of our Negroes launch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off a little Boat, that was by chance there, made to her, and brought her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore. Beſides the kill'd and wounded, there were Eight and twenty Men in her, among whom were two <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Friars, one of which had receiv'd a ſmall hurt in his Arm: By theſe Priſoners I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103058:31"/>
that the Galleons were at <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> of which I had no certain Account ſince my coming out. They had been there ever ſince the end of <hi>October,</hi> and were expected every moment at <hi>Carthage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> their ſtay at <hi>Porto Bello</hi> having been contrary to all the Rules of Commerce, much longer than uſual.</p>
            <p>I made uſe of one of theſe Friars, to repreſent unto the Governour, (whom I deſign'd to ſummon) the inſignificancy of his Defence, againſt ſuch unequal Forces, I multiplied them in the Eyes of the Friar, by drawing forth all the Troops in the Wood, and whilſt they amus'd him, I made ſome of them file off through the By-ways, and advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beyond thoſe he had ſeen; the Ammunition, and Train of Artillery, were ſhewed him; inſomuch, that if the Matter had depended on him only, the Fort would have been ſurrender'd at that very inſtant: However, he made uſe of all his Eloquence to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; to whom he carried from me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry honourable Propoſals. He anſwer'd, by my Drummer, That he was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the Condition of Capitulating; but when he was, he would be willing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103058:31"/>
to accept of the Offers I had made him: Moreover, he charg'd the <hi>Franciſcan,</hi> in particular, with many Civilities to me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fort</hi> Man of War return'd to her Station to batter the Fort; but the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets that flew over it, falling into a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Camp, that we deſign'd not to quit, I ſent her Orders to retire, and to the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and S. <hi>Lewis,</hi> going to the ſame work, to return to their firſt Births. The Mortars on Board, and thoſe on Shoar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Fire at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>About two in the Afternoon, two greater <hi>Pereagoes</hi> than that in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, came before the Wind, to land Succours at the Fort, which the Governor of <hi>Carthagena</hi> had been ſollicited to ſend thither, upon finding their miſtake, in believing that my Expedition was upon the Galleons, and to land at <hi>Porto Bello;</hi> and that I durſt not engage upon an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize of that moment, as was the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking of <hi>Carthagena;</hi> but came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only to ſee if the Galleons were there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:103058:32"/>The Adventure and Example of the Morning, inſpir'd ſome of the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> with a Reſolution of doing what the Grenadiers had done: Theſe laſt <hi>Perea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes</hi> having paſs'd ſomething wide from the Poſt of the laſt, drew to the Shoar only when they were pretty near the Fort; theſe <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> at the head of whom may be about twenty Men, that deſerve to be diſtinguiſh'd for their Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, my intention being very far from comprehending them in the Deſcriptions which I make of the others; theſe <hi>Bucca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers,</hi> I ſay, having poſſeſs'd themſelves of ſome little Houſes on the Lake-ſide, made a very great Fire upon the <hi>Perea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes;</hi> the Noiſe brought the Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, <hi>Canette, Gougon,</hi> and ſome other Officers to them, who encouraging this ſmall number of <hi>Buccaniers</hi> accidentally join'd by ſome Soldiers, led them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Fort, to prevent the <hi>Pereagoes</hi> that kept on their way, from landing the Forces on Board them. The other <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> by the Example of the firſt, having taken Arms, ran to the Shoar, where they made an extraordinary Fire; but the place being within Musket-ſhot of the Fort, the Enemy began to fire upon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:103058:32"/>
them; and the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> who are not us'd to engage where there is any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, made the moſt of their Heels, to bring themſelves under ſhelter: I met them in their way, and finding that words were of no weight with them, I lighted on a Cudgel, and with that forc'd them to return to the Poſt they had aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> was ſurpriz'd at this way of carrying Men on, yet conceal'd, in ſilence, the vexation he conceiv'd at the Action. In this ſpace of time, the <hi>Pereagoes,</hi> terrified with the Diſcharge they had ſuſtain'd, were tack'd about, and on their return towards <hi>Carthagena:</hi> The Major-General taking the advantage of this opportunity, poſted himſelf with the ſmall Troop that followed him, at the foot of the Counterſcarp, which the blindneſs of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had left ſo, as it cover'd us from the Fire of the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts. <hi>Canette, Le Cher, Marin,</hi> and <hi>Gougon,</hi> were wounded in this Action; fifteen Soldiers and <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and wounded. <hi>La Mothe,</hi> Enſign of the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> pitch'd his Colours, yet neither his Signal, nor my Blows, were ſufficiently powerful to make his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions advance. I then imagin'd, that by ſuſtaining thoſe that were at the foot of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:103058:33"/>
the Counterſcarp, I might make an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Buſineſs of this accidental At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: So I abandon'd the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> to their Cowardize, and order'd two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Grenadiers, with the Battalion of <hi>de la Chenau</hi> that was at hand, to march: <hi>Levy</hi> put himſelf at their head, and to ſhorten the way, march'd up to his Belly through the Water, and ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd himſelf likewiſe of the foot of the Counterſcarp; at this inſtant <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a Contuſion on the Thigh, by a Cannon-Ball falling among a heap of Stones. The Major-General did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to ſend me word, that the Poſt he had taken might be kept, by cauſing the Troops to march, altho' at the hazard of ſome Men, by reaſon of the Fire which they were to ſuſtain in going to it; but thoſe Men were got to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Meſſenger had ſpoke to me, ſo there was no time for deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it being neceſſary to maintain this Lodgement; becauſe the Counterſcarp almoſt environing the place, through the fault of not being cut ſloping at the foot, afforded ſhelter from the Fire of the Ramparts, and was capable of receiving a greater number of Men than mine. I ſent Major <hi>Theſut</hi> to bring up the Batta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:103058:33"/>
as likewiſe the Ladders, with all imaginable expedition, to be at Hand, in caſe there ſhould be occaſion for them; and as the Battalions came up, ſo they defil'd off to the foot of the Counterſcarp. The Beſieg'd fir'd very briskly, but being oblig'd to expoſe their whole Bodies, that their Shot might not be made too high, and being eaſily reach'd in that poſture, they ſoon bethought themſelves of firing from behind their Defences, and thereby occaſion'd us but very little damage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Du Buiſſon Varenne,</hi> was at the place of our deſcent with two Battalions, who hearing the Noiſe of our Fire, imagin'd we were attacking the place, altho' he knew not in what manner; he made through the Wood, into the place where the two Mortars were rais'd, and by the way of the little Plain, which is but a quarter ſo long as that in the Wood which makes a Circle, he brought us that Supply at the Minute the Beſieged call'd out, They were willing to capitulate, if they might have good Quarter. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd them, That there was good Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them; but that was all: And, that, if they did not immediately throw
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103058:34"/>
their Arms into the Ditch, for an inſtance of their Sincerity to ſurrender, I would continue the ſetting up of my Ladders; after which, they were not to hope for Quarter. Several of them obeyed, and we ſaw the Harquebuzes in the Air, falling into the Ditch. By this being aſſur'd of their intention, I confirm'd the firſt aſſurance of fair Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with my farther Promiſes of good uſage: I requir'd to have the Gate open'd at that inſtant, my Impatience not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with their calling from the place that they were actually at work upon clearing of it: For I was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, that ſome alteration might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by the delay. But to appeaſe me, they let down a Man by a Cord, who came to aſſure me from the Governour, That they us'd the utmoſt diligence to deliver themſelves into my Hands. In a moment of time the Gate was open'd, and old <hi>Sanchez Ximenez,</hi> who had been Governour for above Twenty five Years, came and delivered the Keys into my poſſeſſion. I gave him all the Comfort I could, in the good uſage I ſhewed him, by giving him, and his Officers, their Liberties, and among the reſt to, the Preſident of the Iſle of St. <hi>Martha,</hi> who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103058:34"/>
happen'd to be at that time in the Fort, and to be wounded: Moreover, I permitted the Governour to carry away whatſoever belong'd to him; and the next Day he retir'd, with his Domeſticks and Slaves, to his Country-Houſes, on the other ſide of the Lake.</p>
            <p>This piece of Succeſs did not ſtand me in above Fifty Men, therein compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all the ſeveral Bodies, as Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers, Soldiers, Inhabitants of the Coaſts, Negroes, and <hi>Buccaniers.</hi> The Garriſon being Priſoners of War, were confin'd. <hi>La Roche du Vigier,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Grenadiers, I made Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; to whom, beſides Cannoniers, and other neceſſary Workmen, I left the Soldiers of the Coaſt for his Garriſon. By this I put him into a Condition of defending me, if occaſion were. The Enemies Garriſon did conſiſt of about Three hundred Men, whereof Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Ten remain'd fit for Service, the reſt were either kill'd or wounded in the Bombardment, Cannonading, and Attack.</p>
            <p>On the Seventeenth we re-embark'd all that we had on Shoar, towards the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103058:35"/>
main Sea, and began to work our ſelves into the Lake, but the careful tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſporting of our Ammunition and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion being of the higheſt conſequence, and could only be counted ſafe in the Lake, I reſolv'd not to ſtir, until they were got in: For which Reaſon I was oblig'd to defer our March until the next Day, to the ſecond Fort, that was about two Leagues and a half from us, called St. <hi>Croix;</hi> the taking of which was not leſs neceſſary to enable our Ships to come within Cannon-ſhot of <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena,</hi> than that of <hi>Boccachica,</hi> to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the entrance into the Lake.</p>
            <p>My intention all along was to cut off the Avenues of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> ſo ſoon as it was poſſible, by ſecuring the Poſt of <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe;</hi> to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I had in the Morning ſent away the Brigantin, <hi>Traverſiers,</hi> and Chaloups, neceſſary for the carrying of the <hi>Bucca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers,</hi> which I order'd upon this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, for the Reaſons before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> fearing that a long trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome March might bring his Contuſion into a Wound, refus'd to charge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Command: His Major, that had formerly ſerv'd with thoſe Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103058:35"/>
and was at preſent in a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Employ, ought to have had this Command; but he likewiſe diſtruſted his Health: Thus there was only <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou</hi> left, who was no ways agreeable to them, as well by reaſon of his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, in not having acquir'd on the Coaſt of St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> either the Eſteem or Love of any Body; as likewiſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of his being Lieutenant-Governour in a place where they never make any ſtay; ſo they could not be perſwaded, that he had any Right to command them: However, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary I ſhould make uſe of him, for want of another. I diſpos'd all things for it, deliver'd him his Inſtructions, and even made moſt of them embark in my Preſence; yet no ſooner was my Back turn'd, but he came running with Tears in his Eyes, to demand Juſtice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Inſolence, for preſſing them to go into the Boats, that attended on them, it was murmur'd about, That they did not know him, neither would they obey him: In ſhort, they refus'd to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark; whereupon he took one of them by the Arm, to puſh him into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa, which the Fellow had the Impudence to return, very inſolently. I forthwith
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103058:36"/>
order'd the Delinquent to be ſhew'd to me, and upon the ſpot, I had him tied to a Tree, a Confeſſor was called, a Cloth bound over his Eyes, and the Musketiers were marching to do Juſtice on him; when <hi>Daunou,</hi> whom 'twas very neceſſary for me to reconcile to the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> having before-hand inſtructed him what he was to do, threw himſelf at my Feet, proteſting, he would not riſe, until I had beſtow'd Mercy on the unfortunate Offender. I ſeem'd to be very difficult, upon the Account of good Order; but at length, at the preſſing Deſires of the Company, I gave him his Life. And much trouble there was, to revive the Condemn'd; who could not believe, that it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to be alive again, after the Ceremony of binding his Eyes.</p>
            <p>Being deſirous to put an end to this Affair, I went to the neareſt Veſſel, where Captain <hi>Pierre</hi> was embark'd; who was, as I had been inform'd, the firſt Beginner of the Mutiny; but, in the time of bringing the Fellow to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, he had conſider'd the Matter, and was march'd on Board with his <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniers;</hi> I commanded him to be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:103058:36"/>
dragg'd out, and put into my Canoa, and ordered him to prepare to die: But there appearing from the reſt of the Company, many ſigns of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and Acclamations of, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> I at laſt reſolv'd to forgive the Offence; yet, withal, threatning to decimate them, upon the leaſt Complaint that <hi>Daunou</hi> ſhould make of their misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour.</p>
            <p>This Uſage, ſo different from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jolements they had been accuſtom'd to receive, from thoſe that made uſe of them; did me very good Service, during the whole time they were under me, ſo as to make 'em tolerably obedient to <hi>Daunou;</hi> yet not to the expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Dangers of Fire and Sword: For having without trouble poſſeſs'd themſelves of <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe,</hi> that was utterly abandon'd by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and believing, that upon their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the little Fort of S. <hi>Lazare,</hi> between <hi>La Pouppe,</hi> and <hi>Carthagena,</hi> they might happen to frighten the Garriſon to retire from thence alſo, he propos'd this Attempt to them; but it was to no purpoſe: And in a Council where he did not preſide, they reſolv'd to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:103058:37"/>
my coming, encamp'd in the Wood, at the foot of the Fort; where they got about Thirty Hours before me.</p>
            <p>On the Seventeenth, all the Ships be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn into Order, at the entrance into the Lake, they paſs'd it in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Eighteenth. The <hi>Diep</hi> Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat touch'd; the great many Banks of Sand in the Lake, which our Pilots did not know, was the occaſion we did not advance very much that Day: The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> ran a-ground this Day; but theſe Banks being only Sand and Ouſe, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with a very fine Turf, there was no fear of danger.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, being ſure of having the Ships ſuddenly follow me, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan our March by Break of Day; and for Security againſt all Hazards, took two Days Proviſion with us for the Forces, which was dignified with the Title of the Land-Army: This, after the departure of the Six hundred and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> that were gone to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, and the Garriſon of One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſeventy Men remaining behind us in the Fort of <hi>Boccachica,</hi> might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of about One thouſand ſeven hundred
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:103058:37"/>
Men, not including ſome Sea-men, One hundred and ten Inhabitants of St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingo</hi> form'd into Companies, Fifteen or Twenty Voluntiers, that follow'd <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> and One hundred and eighty Negroes.</p>
            <p>I was oblig'd to defer making uſe of my Sea-men, until the Ships were arriv'd, and had taken their Stations: The ſmallneſs of our Forces was no diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us. The Marines eſpecially, being highly pleas'd with the execution of a Buſineſs, in which they had never before been employ'd, did apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all imaginable Diligence and Good-will, every one of them chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undertaking whatſoever was appointed to him.</p>
            <p>After we had croſs'd the Mountains covered with Woods, which the Negroes examin'd before us, we met with the Plain, that is here and there cover'd with Shrub-wood, and at Noon came to an old ruin'd Caſtle, within half a Mile of St. <hi>Croix:</hi> Here we reſted the Troops; and beſides the Pits, that are there eaſily made in the Sand, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford indifferent good Water, we had
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:103058:38"/>
the good Fortune to find a great Ciſtern that was a mighty Conveniency to us. After this Refreſhment, the Vicount <hi>de Coetlogon,</hi> whoſe Day it was, march'd on with a part of the Grenadiers, to obſerve how we might encamp as near as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Fort, and to ſeize upon the Paſſages that are in thoſe Marſhes, that encompaſs the Fort; in the mean time we continu'd our March, not being able to leave the Shoar, becauſe the Lake ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, in divers places, within a few paces of the Sea, permits you the choice of that way only, until we came down from the Mountains, below which the Iſland is pretty ſpacious. This way having brought us within Cannon-ſhot of the Baſtion of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> called S. <hi>Domingo,</hi> we ſtruck ſhort off to the right, by a way that the Marſh leaves croſs the low Woods, called <hi>Maugliers,</hi> that grow in the Water.</p>
            <p>In this place I was informed by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers that <hi>Coetlogon</hi> ſent me, that he was at the foot of Fort S. <hi>Croix,</hi> which the Enemy had abandon'd, having carried off their Cannon, and ſet fire to the Lodgements that were there; likewiſe, that ſome part of the Forces might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:103058:38"/>
upon a Spot of Ground about the Fort, but that the reſt muſt be left in the way worn near the Fort by a Rill of Water running from the neighbouring Marſhes; that the bottom was good, and the Water not above Knee-deep, which would no ways prevent a communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Levy,</hi> the Major-General, and my ſelf, with ſome Grenadiers, were in the mean time ſo near advanc'd to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> as eaſily to obſerve, that the place could not be attack'd on one ſide, the Marſhes and Sea not leaving there a Sandy ſpace of about twenty Fathom over, which was expos'd to the fire of three Baſtions; beſides, there was no ſinking two Foot deep, without being in Water. The great Number of People that we ſaw on the Ramparts, who quietly look'd on us, made me deſirous to ſummon them; the Governour was there, and anſwer'd my Drum, That he was ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf better than we could attack him.</p>
            <p>We could not exactly diſcern the foot of the Rampart; and being deſirous to know, if there was a Ditch, I order'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:103058:39"/>
               <hi>De Breſme,</hi> whoſe Battalion was encamp'd at the leaſt diſtance from it, to examine at Night how it was; which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd very well, and aſſur'd me, That the Water of the Marſh went up even to the foot of the Walls, and that there was only a ſmall dry ſpace of Sand, that environ'd part of the great Baſtion called S. <hi>Domingo,</hi> and that on the other ſide, the Sea came up to the foot of this Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. This Report made us conclude, not to attack <hi>Carthagena</hi> in this place.</p>
            <p>The next Day, being the Nineteenth, ſo ſoon as it was Day, we croſs'd the Lake, with much diligence: <hi>Pally,</hi> that commanded the Negroes, whom I had order'd to ſeek out a convenient place of deſcent, having aſſur'd me, that he had found out two, which came almoſt up to the great way; I immediately paſs'd over with <hi>Levy, Sorel,</hi> and the Grena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Battalion of <hi>de la Chenau,</hi> being conducted by ſome Priſoners, that <hi>Pally</hi> had taken on Board of a <hi>Perea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe,</hi> which had endeavour'd to get from <hi>Carthagena:</hi> Theſe Priſoners, in hopes of being the better treated, had offer'd themſelves for our Guides; and, indeed, led us very nigh to the foot of the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:103058:39"/>
upon which Fort St. <hi>Lazare</hi> is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated. At this place we found the <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniers, (Daunou</hi> had left a Detachment of 'em to guard <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe) Coetlogon, La Motte Michel,</hi> and <hi>La Motte d'Heran,</hi> whom I had left at S. <hi>Croix,</hi> to bring away the reſt of the Troops, as the Chaloups came to them; inſomuch, that we were all got together by Break of Day next Morning, leaving only a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant, and Twenty Men, in Fort S. <hi>Croix,</hi> with Orders to keep the Gate always ſhut, that and the Situation being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to prevent the Enemy from repoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves of it.</p>
            <p>We had in the Evening of the Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Day, view'd all the places adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to St. <hi>Lazare,</hi> and perceiv'd, that without getting it into our poſſeſſion, it would not be poſſible to advance a ſtep towards <hi>Carthagena,</hi> by reaſon it commands all the Avenues: We beheld, with much trouble, the time it muſt coſt us, if we attack'd it in Form, and brought our Artillery to batter it. This whole little Mountain is defended with a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Glacis, very ſteep, cover'd with Shrub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, which runs up to the foot of the Wall, where we ſuppos'd was a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:103058:40"/>
Ditch; the Wood being extreamly thick, and very difficult to paſs, prevented us from going to it; upon which I order'd the Chevalier <hi>de Pointis,</hi> to ſeek out two Negroes to examine the Matter; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to what purpoſe I ſent for them, he betook himſelf to the Wood, at the ſame time he ſent them to me; which he croſs'd in the beſt manner he could, until he took hold of the very Wall; the Negroes went almoſt as faſt as he, and then came to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me, that the Ground was level to the foot of the Fort: The Chevalier <hi>de Pointis</hi> quietly heard their Report, which being exactly true, he ſaid not a word of what he had done. In all this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there was only a Grenadier kill'd upon our return.</p>
            <p>Upon the next Day, being the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth, <hi>Levy, Coetlogon,</hi> and <hi>Sorel,</hi> having got up to an Eminency, that was above all the others, ſent to me, to come to them; from whence they ſhewed me, that the Fort did not take up (as we had imagin'd) all the Eminency, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a good diſtance farther to the right; and, that if we could make a Way, through the Wood, to that heighth,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:103058:40"/>
we might afterwards go upon a level from thence to the foot of the Fort, all the way, being cover'd with Woods; and that we could fix a Miner to it, if the Garriſon ſhould reſolve not to quit it. Upon this, I order'd the Major-General to call to Arms, and having call'd the Negroes to me at the moment I came down, I put them to work upon cutting of a Way, to facilitate the March of the Troops; this was carried on half way up the Hill, where dividing the Way, to encompaſs the Fort, <hi>Levy</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the right, <hi>Coetlogon</hi> to the left, and the Major-General viſited every place as his Preſence was requiſite. This Work being found ſhorter than what we had expected, we arriv'd at the foot of the Fort in a very little time, where we made the greateſt Fire that was poſſible for us to make, at the ſame time calling out for the Ladders; not that we expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to uſe them, but to terrifie the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; however, I ſent for the Miner in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>During which time, the Enemy made no great Fire, by reaſon we made our Shot upon them, ſo ſoon as they expos'd their Bodies to view. They had for a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:103058:41"/>
good while perceiv'd, that we were pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing through the Wood; and we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, by the ſounding of a Bell, how much every ſtep we made increas'd their trouble. This Bell was a Signal to the City, to acquaint them with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; at firſt it ſtruck only now and then, keeping ſounding more and more by degrees, until at length it rung full out, when their fear gave them occaſion to think they would be attack'd on all ſides; which had effectually happen'd, if they had not choſe rather to retire, for the Quarter towards the Gate was then free to them.</p>
            <p>In this manner we poſſeſs'd our ſelves of the Fort: In the place there was only nine kill'd and wounded. On our ſide, the Chevalier <hi>de Vezins,</hi> that commanded the Grenadiers, ſince <hi>La Roche du Vigier</hi> was made Governour of <hi>Boccachica,</hi> was kill'd, with five Grenadiers; <hi>Simmonet,</hi> Colonel of a Battalion, dangerouſly hurt in the Head, and St. <hi>Lazare,</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain of Grenadiers, wounded in the Thigh.</p>
            <p>The taking of St. <hi>Lazare,</hi> giving us the liberty to open our ſelves, we croſs'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103058:41"/>
the way, and advanc'd our Camp to the Chappel of St. <hi>Lazare</hi> Hoſpital, which is a great breadth; being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd on one ſide, with ſeveral little Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, that have a communication with the Lake; and on the other, by a high thick Wall, which beſides the Trees that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd us, did prevent the Baſtions of the City from diſcerning the place we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd; the kill'd and wounded that we had, were only by chance Balls: In the mean time, this little Chappel gave us the opportunity of going cover'd within a ſmall Musket-ſhot of the place, which is not above that diſtance from it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt we were thus employ'd, the Ships, by the care of <hi>Du Buiſſon,</hi> were come nearer to the Town; inſomuch, that in the Morning, a Bomb-Galliot with a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and a <hi>Traverſier,</hi> were moor'd, and began to fire. In the Evening the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſier</hi> was oblig'd to retire, being ſhot through with ſeveral Balls, and ready to ſink; <hi>Bois Pinault,</hi> Lieutenant of the Artillery, commanded her; <hi>De Mons</hi> was in the Galliot, which likewiſe ſuffer'd ſo much, that ſhe was alſo oblig'd to retire a little; beſides, ſhe had a great many kill'd on Board her; but the ſtrength of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:103058:42"/>
theſe Veſſels enabling them to endure a great deal of Fire, ſhe began again in the Morning of the Twenty firſt of the ſame Month.</p>
            <p>My chief Ingenier was wounded, and ill; whereby I was oblig'd to execute that Function. The Officers of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, which I had form'd into Brigades, had only their own Readineſs to enable them to execute every thing, which could not ſupply the want of Practice and Judgment. I had, by good Luck, at the firſt, agreed with the Major-General, where to begin the Opening and Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Trenches. I had, moreover, deſign'd the Batteries of Cannons and Mortars, and given Orders for the things neceſſary to the Works; by which means, the Accident that happen'd to me a few Hours afterwards, did not much inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our Proceedings: In the mean time, all Hands were at work, the Soldiers upon Faſcines and Gabions, the Sea-men upon landing the Artillery; in the drawing of which, the Hundred and eighty Negroes were a mighty aſſiſtance to us: For as to the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> we were never able to make the leaſt uſe of them; and the ſhare which they ought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:103058:42"/>
to have perform'd of the Work, falling upon others, who were by this means over-wrought, did not a little contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the cauſing of thoſe Diſtempers, which ſo lamentably reign'd among us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
            <p>Our ſmall number, and the great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to be done, forc'd us to keep the Troops with their Arms in one hand, and their Working-Tools in the other, the Soldiers were at one and the ſame time, both on the Guard, and working; the nearneſs of the Woods, on whoſe ſides we were encamp'd, were a great conveniency to us: For when we drew out our Troops, they left their Arms upon that ſpot, and went to the Wood with their Tools; and upon the firſt Beat of Drum, they quitted their Tools, and running to their Arms, were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in a Condition of marching; the Battalion of Grenadiers, was ever at the Head of the Camp, to ſuſtain what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever might be preſented; and that was ſufficient, by reaſon the diſpoſition of the Ground was ſuch, that the Camp was on all parts inacceſſible, but on that only towards the City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:103058:43"/>Nor were they leſs diligent on Board the Fleet: <hi>Du Buiſſon</hi> caus'd the <hi>Scepter</hi> to advance, commanded by <hi>Guilotin,</hi> the Saint <hi>Lewis</hi> by <hi>Sabran,</hi> and the <hi>Vermandois,</hi> aboard which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; with theſe Ships he made up towards the City, notwithſtanding the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had purpoſely ſunk a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon to render the paſſage difficult: We were oblig'd to leave on Board theſe Ships that were to fight, a great many Sea-men to work the Guns; which diminiſh'd the number of thoſe employ'd upon the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imbarkment, and tranſporting of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery that was neceſſary to us on Shoar: It is hardly to be imagin'd, how ſo ſmall a parcel of our Men was able, in ſix Days to diſimbark, draw half a League upon Land, and bring into a State of Battery, Twenty ſeven of the greateſt Cannon we uſed, five Mortars, and all the Equipage neceſſary to the execution of both the one and the other, beſides the Proviſions that we were oblig'd to bring to the Camp; but it is true, that <hi>Du Tilleul</hi> being charg'd with this Care, attended it with ſuch application, that making uſe of the Sea-men only at certain Intervals, he conſtantly kept our Magazines fill'd with Proviſion and Ammunition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:103058:43"/>
ever interrupting any other Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Our Affairs being in this State, and having, moreover, rais'd a Mortar to prevent the Enemy from going on with a Work, that we perceiv'd they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun upon a Platform over the Gate: We having twice neglected to throw up a Breaſt-work that I had mark'd out; and fearing, leaſt at the third time there might not be ſomething farther neceſſary to be done, that might occaſion a delay, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to continue my Preſence there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it was perfected; my ſtay inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately brought a great many Officers, this number of People being moreover re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable for their Cloaths, drew upon us the Enemies Fire, and particularly that of their Cannon, with Hail-ſhot, by which I was wounded; my hurt was more painful than dangerous, yet I was very fearful that this Accident might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our Men, which indeed was too apparent at firſt: Moreover, I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, leaſt the Officers, whom I had by good Fortune maintain'd in a perfect Union hitherto, ſhould not continue the ſame, which would have been detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to our Deſign: I reſolv'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:103058:44"/>
to ſtruggle with the Pain which I felt; inſomuch, that after the Third Day I was carried into every part that I could have viſited in another Condition: But during that interval, I committed all things that I could not inſpect, to the Care of <hi>Levy;</hi> who certainly acquitted himſelf to a degree above all manner of Praiſe; indefatigable, full of Expedients and Contrivances for the Work; neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his Reſt, and his Meals; he was every-where, and forwarded every thing, with an incredible vigour.</p>
            <p>The Vicount <hi>de Coetlogon,</hi> was to have commanded the Artillery; but I was over-joyed to underſtand, that his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations were rather to enter, with the reſt, into the general Service; this gave me an opportunity of chooſing ſeveral Perſons, to manage the Artillery, who did their Duty with more expedition than would have been poſſible for any ſingle Man to have done: So he had the Guard only of the Battery of five Cannons of Twelve and Eighteen Pounders, which he rais'd at the foot of Fort St. <hi>Lazare;</hi> in which Fort we had got mounted Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Pieces of Twelve, Eight, and Six, that terribly ſhatter'd the Baſtions of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:103058:44"/>
place. <hi>Mornay,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Pont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chartrain,</hi> was in the Fort with his Ship's Company; the Chevalier <hi>De la Motte d'Heran,</hi> took upon him the Care of a great Battery of nine Guns, that was likewiſe upon the ſame Eminency with the Fort, but more to the right than the firſt: <hi>La Motte Michel,</hi> had the Charge of that we called, <hi>The Royal Battery,</hi> conſiſting of ſix Pieces of Thirty ſix, and Twenty four, planted Sixty Fathoms diſtant from the Gate, and deſigned to make the Breach: <hi>Gombaud</hi> play'd the Mortars, which he had been exercis'd in from his Youth, and doubtleſs never any did better execution than theſe; for one would have thought the Bombs had been plac'd by Hand, in the places where they were deſign'd to fall. Theſe Mortars were plac'd between the Batteries of the Cannon, in ſuch manner, that as ſoon as they began to play, the place was on fire in ſeveral parts at once; the Galliot was at work on her ſide, but the Bombs ſhe ſpent the firſt Days, were of little or no effect.</p>
            <p>The Twenty firſt, Twenty ſecond, Twenty third, and Twenty fourth, were employ'd in tranſporting the Cannon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:103058:45"/>
and getting together the things neceſſary; the <hi>Vermandois</hi> only was advanc'd to Cannonade the Town; but I being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, that ſhe being alone, did ſolely bear the whole Fire of a Baſtion, that could conveniently reach her; I order'd her to retire, and to wait for the other Ships that were to go on with her; we were likewiſe conſtrain'd to bring away two ſmall Cannons that we had rais'd in the Chappel of St. <hi>Lazare,</hi> without any other Parapet than the Wall, upon which the Enemy making an extraordinary Fire, render'd this Poſt untenable, we brought off the Cannon with the loſs of eight or ten Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Canette,</hi> altho' wounded, return'd to the Camp on this Day, being the Twenty fourth; and I continu'd to regulate, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Bed, with him, what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be done. In the Evening of the ſame Day, he open'd the Trench a little below the Door of the Chappel of St. <hi>Lazare,</hi> where we were under cover, being the ſame place I had agreed upon with the Major-General. <hi>Levy,</hi> whoſe Day it was, did not Command, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he was entruſted with the General Management of the Siege in my ſtead:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:103058:45"/>
               <hi>Coetlogon</hi> mounted the Guard in the Trench, which was advanc'd the ſame Night Seventy two Fathoms, being as far as was neceſſary to attack the City-Gate, when the Breach ſhould be perfectly made. The following Days the Captains took their turns, according to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and mounted every Twenty four Hours; the Batteries were likewiſe brought into a condition for Service, and on the Twenty eighth begun to play, our Fire, until then, being only from ſome little Pieces that were mounted in haſte. The Enemies Fire, which had always been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moderate, grew now ſomething ſlower; for the Bombs, and the Cannon of the Fort, and the Hill, had diſmounted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of their Pieces; yet they troubled us leſs with their Sallies, for they did not ſo much as attempt to make one in the whole Siege.</p>
            <p>At this time, a Bark ſent from <hi>Porto Bello,</hi> by the General of the Galleons, to the Governour of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what paſs'd in this place, came qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly into <hi>Boccachica,</hi> and fell into the hands of the <hi>Avenant,</hi> and <hi>Marin,</hi> that I had left there, who took her with their Canoes: The Letters on Board her,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:103058:46"/>
were in Anſwer to thoſe which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Carthagena</hi> had ſent to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, informing him, that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet was upon the Coaſt; they contain'd a particular of the Precautions that were us'd to ſecure the Galleons, <hi>viz.</hi> By bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the very lower end of the Port, and defending the approach to them by an Eſtoccade of Piles, and Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms of Cannon: They added farther, That part of the Silver which they had, was already brought into the Caſtles; for that they had ſuſpended their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of ſending it back to <hi>Panama,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they had received ſome farther Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Deſigns; which the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral preſs'd the Governour to ſend him immediately, either by the ſame Bark, or a ſecond, that was to come away in Four and twenty Hours after the firſt: But what moſt acquainted us with the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Condition they were in, was the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Deſires of the General, in the moſt preſſing Terms, to ſend him fifty Pullets, and ſome Quintals of white Biskit.</p>
            <p>Altho' the Batteries, as I ſaid, were not in a Condition to fire, until the Twenty eighth, yet that deſign'd to make the Breach, was play'd ſo ſucceſsfully,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:103058:46"/>
by <hi>La Motte Michel, Siglas, Longjoue,</hi> and ſome other Officers under him, aſſiſted by the Gunner of the <hi>Scepter,</hi> that on the Twenty ninth in the Morning, the Wall ſeem'd to totter; our Fire had not been diſcontinued, becauſe of the Night, but it increas'd ſo much in the Day, that in the Evening the Front of the Rampart being quite fall'n down, <hi>Levy,</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,</hi> who would loſe no time, imagin'd the Breach was paſſable, and came to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Aſſault to me. I was reſolv'd neither to loſe, nor neglect a Minute; but likewiſe determin'd not to hazard any thing upon ill Grounds: I order'd to Arms, and diſpos'd all things for an Aſſault; yet reſolving not to engage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I judg'd it feaſible: In ſhort, Night being come, whilſt we prepar'd our ſelves, the Chevalier <hi>de Pointis</hi> paſſing up to the Arm-pits in Water, over the little Marſh upon which the Cauſey, and the Bridge, that communicates with the City, are built, went to view the Breach. He aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd me, That the Wall was indeed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much ruin'd; but that it was not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as yet, to mount it without Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:103058:47"/>The Chevalier <hi>de Ferriere,</hi> Captain of a Fire-ſhip, who was at the Head of the Brigade of Ingeniers, that I had ſent to obſerve the Condition of the wooden Bridge, (which the Enemy had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to blow up, by running under it a <hi>Pereagoe</hi> fill'd with Powder) brought me word, That the Bridge had ſuffer'd; yet might not be altogether unſerviceable to us: And, that the Gate beyond it, which we imagin'd was beat down by the Cannon, was ſtrongly terraſs'd on the inſide; of this he was poſitively cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by reaſon he had put his Hand into the Holes which the Cannon had made, and therefore there was no hopes of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the place by that; but that the Breach muſt be paſs'd, to the foot of which he could not get from the place where he was; and that it was, by all that he could perceive in the Night, but little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Officers were too well known, to doubt of their having been where they ſaid they were: Moreover, <hi>Canette</hi> told me, he was not quite ready; that all the Gabions, and Faſcines, which he had got together, were ſpent; and,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:103058:47"/>
that if by chance we ſhould find ſo much reſiſtance as to be oblig'd to lodge upon the Breach, we ſhould not be able to do it, our Earth-ſacks being at the Lake-ſide, for want of Hands to bring them; that there were two little Flanks unruin'd, that would deſtroy a great many Men in the Attack; all theſe Reaſons engag'd me to diſmiſs the Troops from their Duty, and we agreed not to make the Aſſault until the firſt of the next Month; in the mean time, to employ both Night and Day in the finiſhing of the Breach, and to get together all ſuch things as would be neceſſary upon that occaſion.</p>
            <p>Upon the Twenty ninth, <hi>Du Buiſſon</hi> being advanc'd with the three Ships, <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter,</hi> St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and <hi>Vermandois,</hi> within a ſmall Cannon-ſhot of the City, they fir'd upon it with all their Artillery; but ſeeing it only reach'd the tops of the Houſes, and my Buſineſs being to have two Baſtions ſilenc'd that annoy'd my Camp, I ſent to let them know, That when they were retired in the Evening, they ſhould wait new Orders before they begun again.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:103058:48"/>In the mean time, we prepar'd our ſelves for the Buſineſs of the next Day; the Order of Attack I had regulated with the Major-General, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</p>
            <p>A Serjeant, with ten Grenadiers, ſhould begin, ſuſtained by the Company of Grenadiers on Guard, there being always one at the Head of the Trench; the whole Body of Grenadiers were likewiſe to advance to the Head of it, to ſuſtain the firſt, and to precede a Battalion, in whoſe Rear ſhould be <hi>Canette,</hi> the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Ferriere, du Crest, Courſy,</hi> and One hundred and fifty Workmen, with the Sub-Ingeniers, and all neceſſary Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements; after whom ſhould follow the ſame number of <hi>Buccaniers</hi> and Negroes. The Head of the Trench was twenty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom diſtant from the little Ravelin, that in ſome ſort covers the Bridge, whoſe Wall was ſo low, that it might have been paſs'd, if it had not been eaſier to paſs through a ſingle Barrier that was there, and theſe Troops fill'd all the Trench, unto the Gate of the Chappel: All the reſt of the Battali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were poſted according to their
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:103058:48"/>
Ranks, within the Cloſe of the Hoſpital, to march into the Trench as faſt as the firſt Troops advanc'd out of it, to the Attack, and to follow 'em up, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain 'em. I recommended to Major <hi>Theſut,</hi> in particular, the good Order which theſe Battalions were to obſerve, to the end, that too much Precipitation might not cauſe Confuſion in their March, nor too much Slowneſs occaſion as much Inconveniency by any Interval being left open.</p>
            <p>All things were thus regulated for the next Day, when <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> whoſe Day it was, came to tell me, about Three a Clock, That he ſaw the Breach from the Head of the Trench, plainly enough to aſſure me, that it was paſſable; that he believ'd the Enemies were at work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, in throwing up a Retrenchment. A delay, in this caſe, would have been ſo very inconvenient to me, by reaſon of the time I ſhould have given the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to finiſh their Work, that I forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with reſolv'd to attack the Enemies at that inſtant, provided I found the Breach to be as it was deſcrib'd to me. I was the more inclin'd to believe it, by being inform'd on all Hands, in the Morning,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:103058:49"/>
with the good Effects of <hi>the Royal Battery,</hi> which at every Diſcharge brought pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Ruines from the Wall; and, at the worſt, I could not be more aſham'd in retiring, if things ſhould not appear in the Condition reported, than I had been the Night before.</p>
            <p>I immediately ſent for <hi>Levy,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor-General, <hi>Canette,</hi> and ſome other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, that were gone to <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Pouppe,</hi> to diſcover from that place the Condition of the Town; but hearing a general Alarm beaten, they preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd; and being inform'd what was to be done, every one of them ran to give the neceſſary Orders to what belong'd to him. The Troops at work in the Woods, being called by the Drums, inſtantly came to their Arms, and put themſelves into order; there was only a ſmall Body in the Trench, that were not exactly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced where they were to be; but the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor-General diſpos'd of them with all poſſible Expedition: At which time <hi>Neſmond, Poullermont, La Linde, Du Che,</hi> and <hi>Rochebonne,</hi> who (as I ſaid before) choſe rather to ſerve as my <hi>Aids de Camps,</hi> than to be employ'd in any other Service, not knowing but that the Troops were
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:103058:49"/>
in perfect order, came to acquaint me, That every thing was ready, and that they waited for my Orders to march: I gave it, imagining like the reſt, that all the Wall was fall'n.</p>
            <p>The Order was immediately carried by my <hi>Aids de Camp;</hi> who having all undertaken to deliver it, took that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to run to the head of the Trench, <hi>Du Tilleul</hi> only, that could not be any where elſe, was with me; <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> was on his Day in the Trench; but <hi>Levy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eldeſt of all, and this Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing regarded as a General Affair, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon all were employed in it, put himſelf at the Head, and gave the Motion to the Troops to begin, at the moment he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Order; which was as ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed, as it was ſpeedily carried.</p>
            <p>What ought to have been a great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, had like to have caus'd a great Inconveniency; the Officers, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Remonſtrances that had been made them, upon the neceſſity of each of them being at his Poſt, to ſee the Troops perform their Duty; carried on by their Courage, the greateſt part of them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced before the Troops, and aſſaulted
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:103058:50"/>
the Breach with Sword in Hand, without obſerving how they were follow'd; and the Troops, unprovided of Leaders, did indeed march on, but ſlower than the Safety of their Officers requir'd, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd for a conſiderable time expos'd upon the Breach which they had gain'd. We were all deceiv'd in our Reckoning, for it was the ſteepeſt way imaginable: The Grenadiers, who were order'd not to fire, could not abſtain from it, when they came to be expos'd out of the Trench, and to ſuffer the Fire of the Ramparts; but the time they employ'd to Re-charge, detaining them in the way between the Trench and the Breach, was the reaſon of their Officers being alone at the top: <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> repair'd the inconveniency of this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident ſo ſoon as it was poſſible, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening on the Troops, as likewiſe by his Words and his Actions. In the mean time, the Chevalier de <hi>Pointis,</hi> who had firſt mounted, was in an inſtant joyn'd by <hi>Gougon, Jaucourt,</hi> and <hi>Marolles,</hi> whoſe Battalion was on the Trench-Guard; <hi>Daye, Vignancourt, Montroſier, Du Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Vaujoux,</hi> young <hi>Marolles, Marigny, Fouilleuſe,</hi> and my <hi>Aids de Camp:</hi> They endeavour'd to maintain themſelves, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Efforts of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:103058:50"/>
who were attack'd at the time they leaſt expected it; yet not being diſmayed, they attempted to drive us off with Sword and Pike. <hi>Marolles,</hi> and <hi>Du Rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> were already mortally wounded, and upon the Ground; <hi>Fouilleuſe</hi> had his Leg broke, <hi>Gougon, Montroſier,</hi> young <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles, Marigny, Daye,</hi> and <hi>Mouſſac,</hi> were all wounded; ſome ſhot, others hurt with Pikes; ſome of them had ſeveral Wounds, as <hi>Montroſier,</hi> and <hi>Vaujoux;</hi> when at length <hi>Levy,</hi> and the Grenadiers, came to their aſſiſtance, and repuls'd the Enemy; who rallying nevertheleſs at the end of the Streets, were ſeveral times charg'd before they could be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven off. <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> not ſo nimble as the reſt, altho' one of the firſt at the foot of the Breach, maugre all his Good-will, had ſo much trouble to climb it, that he was out of Breath by that time he got to the top, where he thought he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recover his Wind. He was follow'd by fifteen or twenty Voluntiers, Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Coaſt, who did very good Service; for firing upon ſuch of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies as were yet upon the Ramparts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind two little Flankers that fir'd upon the Bridge, and very much annoy'd our Troops; they at length oblig'd them to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:103058:51"/>
follow thoſe that were driven from the Platform, where the Breach ended; the Major-General, who at the bottom of the Breach was wounded by a Musket-Ball in the Neck, follow'd by <hi>Baraudin,</hi> one of his Aids, and <hi>Francin,</hi> Captain of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers with his Arm broken, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding mounted the Breach together; but the Captain's ſtrength failing, ſo ſoon as he was up, he was forc'd to be brought off, for the ſame reaſon the Major-General was not able to make a much longer ſtay.</p>
            <p>All the Troops defiling in the mean time one after another, I found my ſelf at laſt rid of all Uneaſineſs for the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of an Action, that may, with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, be term'd very bold, and very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, for Seafaring Men.</p>
            <p>A Party of the Negroes of <hi>Pally,</hi> who conducted them, in defiling off to the Ramparts on the left, puſh'd the Enemy from Baſtion to Baſtion, unto the Cauſey that divides this part of the City, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly called <hi>Hihimani,</hi> from the other call'd by the general Name of <hi>Carthagena;</hi> but the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> to exempt themſelves from the Attack of the Breach, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:103058:51"/>
the Matter upon the Bridge, and the little Cauſey of <hi>Hihimani,</hi> and reſolv'd to line the Hedge over-againſt the Ramparts, where they made an extraordinary Fire, not perceiving the part they choſe out of fear, was much more dangerous than that they endeavour'd to avoid: But by good Fortune for them, the Enemy was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from off thoſe Ramparts, and thoſe <hi>Indian</hi> Heroes adventur'd to enter, when they thought the Buſineſs was pretty well at an end; yet were they a little miſtaken in this Account: For the Enemy, after having ſtood firm at all the Corners of the Streets, were at length driven to the Cauſey of <hi>Hihimani,</hi> towards <hi>Carthagena,</hi> into which they deſigned to retreat; but the Governour, who perhaps fear'd, that upon opening the Gates we might enter Pell-mell with his People, plainly told them, That he would not let them in, until they had attack'd us in <hi>Hihimani:</hi> So after the loſs of about 800 Men, urg'd by neceſſity, and poſſibly the Wine they had drunk, infuſing freſh Courage into them; they got together in a Croud, and with a great Cry came and charg'd us at the Head of the great Street, which ends at the Cauſey: We had juſt begun to caſt up a Retrenchment there, and the Troops
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:103058:52"/>
not having time to bring themſelves into Order, ſurpriz'd with this Attack, mov'd a little backwards, to cover themſelves with the Houſes of the Streets which croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that: But while <hi>Levy,</hi> and the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, brought them into order, which was inſtantly done, <hi>Vignancourt,</hi> the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>de Pointis, Gougon,</hi> and <hi>Jaucourt,</hi> with a ſmall number of Grenadiers, ſuſtain'd this impetuous Attack; but the Troops being brought back to the Charge, made a very great ſlaughter of the Enemies; above 150 were found the next Day upon the Cauſey, pierc'd with Bayonets, beſides thoſe that went off wounded: In this Charge the Vicount <hi>de Coetlogon</hi> was wounded with a Musket-Ball in the Shoulder, who was come hither from the Battery, accompanied by <hi>De la Motte Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> and <hi>De la Motte d'Heran;</hi> his Wound did not at firſt appear to be conſiderable, but by weakning of him, it contributed to his Death, caus'd by a malignant Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and here the Chevalier <hi>de Pointis,</hi> after having paſs'd through ſo many Dangers, to which he expos'd himſelf, received the Wound he died of; the Marquis <hi>Du Boury</hi> was at this time likewiſe hurt in his Face, St. <hi>Amant</hi> on the Side, and many other Officers received Contuſions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:103058:52"/>The Enemy being drove back again were received by a little Port into <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena;</hi> we applied our ſelves in <hi>Hihimani,</hi> to making of Retrenchments at all the Avenues, to ſecure us from Surprizes, and to permit our Troops to paſs the Night quietly, in the convenient Lodgings of a handſome City; the Fire of the Enemies Cannon kill'd ſome Men in this Work, that were commanded by the Chevalier <hi>de la Ferriere, du Crest,</hi> and <hi>Courſy,</hi> under the direction of <hi>Canette,</hi> about Ten at Night all was in good order.</p>
            <p>In this Action I loſt about ſixty Men, and had ſome more than that number wounded, without comprehending the Officers before-mentioned.</p>
            <p>It was reſolv'd to reſt the Troops, the next Day being the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> and to work only upon the opening of the Gate, and repairing of the Bridge for the paſſage of the great Cannon, with which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to beat down the Rampart we had to paſs, before we could enter into the other part of the City. <hi>Canette</hi> went in the Morning early, to view the places of Battery that were to be rais'd, and having
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:103058:53"/>
ſhew'd them to me in the Evening, I found them ſo near the Wall, that I did not doubt making a very conſiderable Breach in a very little time; this whole Cauſey, and that part of the Marſh which divides <hi>Carthagena,</hi> are not a Musket-ſhot over.</p>
            <p>This Day I ſent on Board the <hi>Scepter,</hi> St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the <hi>Vermandois,</hi> a part of the Detachment of Sea-men, call'd Scythe-men, by reaſon of the ſmall Scythes fix'd upon Staffs, which they had for their Arms; I order'd theſe Ships to endeavour again the next Day, to ruine the Defences of a Baſtion that could hurt us more than the others. About Three a Clock, on the Second, they began to Cannonade; in the mean time we put all things into a readineſs, towards the bringing of the great Cannon into <hi>Hihimani;</hi> this Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonading continu'd until Six; when at the ſight of four white Flags flying, two on <hi>Hihimani</hi> ſide, and the others towards the Sea, I order'd the Ships to forbear firing, until I knew the Intentions of the Beſieg'd. They told <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> who by the means of a little <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> run himſelf into all things, That they were willing to capitulate upon honourable Terms. I ſent them word, That before I enter'd
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:103058:53"/>
upon it, I expected Hoſtages that very moment, without giving any other Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance than my Parole, to return them the next Day, in caſe we did not agree upon Terms. This hard Condition was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; which plainly ſhewed me, that the Enemies were ſtraiten'd. In ſhort, the Precedent of <hi>Hihimani</hi> terrified them, and the Bombs permitted them no manner of reſt; ſo they brought me two of the moſt conſiderable Men amongſt them. At this inſtant I received Advice from two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of 1000, or 1200 Men, being upon their March to throw themſelves into <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena:</hi> An <hi>Indian</hi> was the firſt that brought me this Account; which was afterwards confirmed to me, by a Letter from a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant at <hi>Boccachica;</hi> who ſeeking for freſh Proviſions in the Country, had been beſieg'd in one of the Houſes of Don <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez Ximenez,</hi> defended by his People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſmall Detachment of that Body on their March. The <hi>Indian</hi> ſaid, That he had been among the Troops; who knowing that we poſſeſs'd the common High-way, did deſign to go round the great Lake, and paſſing afterwards through By-ways into the little Lakes that lie about <hi>Carthagena,</hi> to go on a long the Sea-ſide, and get into the City by the Baſtions of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:103058:54"/>
St. <hi>Catherine.</hi> I immediately order'd a-ſhoar all the Scythe-men, and Sea-men, that could poſſibly be ſpar'd, who were alſo provided with Arms; theſe were ſet to guard the Batteries, for all the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery was as yet there. I detach'd <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> with 500 <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> and a Battalion of 300 Soldiers, to ſtop the paſſage of theſe Succours; he poſted himſelf amongſt the little Lakes, where the Enemies would be oblig'd to come; and the advantage of the place wherein he was poſted, enabled him to have given a very good Account of them. The next Day I ſent <hi>Daunou</hi> with a leſs number, being inform'd it would be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to repel the Succours, in caſe it ſhould be attempted; but they did not appear, neither did I ever know the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time we were employed upon the Capitulation. <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> ever an importunate Advocate for the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> continually tormented me, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the Conditions I impos'd upon them; but being not only charg'd with the ſupport of the Honour due to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Arms, but having likewiſe my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers Intereſts to manage, I ſtood firm to my Demands, altho' an infinite number
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:103058:54"/>
of Reaſons might have occaſion'd me to be more impatient than any Body elſe, to have this Affair determin'd. At length I propos'd to the Governour, the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Articles of paſſing out through the Breach, with all thoſe carrying Arms, Drums beating, to take four Pieces of Cannon; and as to the reſt, it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That all the Silver, without Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, or Reſerve, in favour of whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it might be, ſhould belong to me; that the Effects of all ſuch as went out, or were abſent, of whatſoever Nature the ſaid Effects were, ſhould devolve to me; that ſuch of the Inhabitants as would continue in the place, excepting their Plate, ſhould enjoy all their Poſſeſſions and Priviledges, and for the future be regarded as the King's Subjects, being they were ſo by Conqueſt: And farther, that all the Churches and Convents ſhould be preſerv'd.</p>
            <p>This Matter agreed on, I demanded until ſuch time as the Governour march'd out, which could not be in ſome Days, that they ſhould deliver me up one of the Gates; which they did, and I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Grenadiers to it. I had regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated what every Man, according to his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:103058:55"/>
Condition, was to carry out with him in Silver for their Subſiſtance; to which, that I might not be impos'd upon, I had added this Condition, That I reſerv'd to my ſelf the liberty of ſearching the Men and Baggage at the Gate. The Governor ſent to deſire I would permit, out of Courteſie, (which was the Expreſſion) the principal Officers, and ſome other conſiderable Perſons that I permitted to follow him, the double of what was ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated. This amounted unto 2000 Crowns a Head; but they being a ſmall number, I readily acquieſc'd to it, and was convinc'd by the Fervency of their Acknowledgments, that it was really ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to them.</p>
            <p>It was of great conſequence to me, that thoſe who were allow'd to retire where they pleas'd, after the Garriſon was march'd out, ſhould remain until they were oblig'd to reveal what Sums they had in their Houſes; therefore I was very exact in my Meaſures, that no Body might eſcape: In the mean time, ſeveral Officers went freely up and down the City; and <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> whom I had declar'd Governour, that they might believe I deſign'd to keep the City, took upon him to deliver to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:103058:55"/>
ſome People Certificates, that were not Paſports, yet had ſome reſemblance to them, by which thoſe People paſs'd the Gates, the Officers on the Guard belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it was my Order. I do believe he had no ill Intention in it, and I did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute that manner of acting to the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he ever affected to ſhew to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards;</hi> yet common Report did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying, that he got very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sums; which I did not believe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I would not have it thought, that I tolerated his Conduct; therefore I forbid him the continuance of it: And this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo much diſpleas'd him, that he never came afterwards to me.</p>
            <p>The Governour delayed his departure all that he could; but at length I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him, That he muſt poſitively march out upon the Sixth, and that on the ſame Day I would enter at the Head of the Troops; which was accordingly executed. The Count <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gnez de los Rios,</hi> follow'd with his Garriſon, being liſted Men, to the number of about 2800, march'd out through a Lane of our Soldiers and Sea-men, (whom I had order'd on Shoar to enlarge the number) <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Coaſt, and Negroes. We
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:103058:56"/>
two were upon our Horſes, and having ſaluted me with his Sword, after ſome Expreſſions of Civility, he continu'd his way with the City-Colours, and two of the four Cannon allowed him, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Equipage convenient for the expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the others; even theſe were the ſmalleſt, and drawn by Men.</p>
            <p>Theſe People were narrowly ſearch'd as they came out; but when I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of their Number, which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt equal to ours; and perceiving that this Search would bring the Night upon us, before we could diſpatch them, I was afraid, leaſt the danger of loſing a little Money, ſhould occaſion ſome diſorder when it was dark; ſo I ſent my Orders to the Gates, to haſten their March, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delaying of it by a Search, which produc'd little; and the Garriſon all marched out before Sun-ſet. It was not without a great deal of trouble, that I continued upon my Horſe, to receive the Salute of the Governour; but that being paſs'd, I was oblig'd through the great pain of my Wound, to get into my Chair, wherein I was us'd to be carried; in this Condition, and in the midſt of the Guards Marine, who were cloath'd
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:103058:56"/>
alike, I went (preceded by a Battalion of Grenadiers) to take poſſeſſion of the City.</p>
            <p>I was well aſſur'd there was Silver in <hi>Carthagena;</hi> but the difficulty was how to get it: The worſt that could happen to thoſe in poſſeſſion of it, was the loſs of it, when we had diſcover'd it; it was therefore neceſſary to ſearch all the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: But by whom could it be done? With what Surety, that the beſt part ſhould not remain undiſcover'd? The number of Officers was not great enough, to diſperſe them into all the neceſſary places; and if I would not have left any thing, it muſt have requir'd me above ſix Months time. In this perplexity I bethought my ſelf of this Expedient: I publickly declar'd, and order'd it to be ſet up in the principal places, That I would give the Tenth to the Proprietors, of whatſoever they honeſtly brought me; and a Tenth to them that ſhould inform me, of any Perſons that did not declare their Effects. To theſe Promiſes I join'd my Threats, of puniſhing them for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:103058:57"/>The hopes of preſerving a part of what was otherwiſe all in danger to be loſt; the fear of Neighbours, and ill Friends, who at the ſame time had the opportunity of profiting and being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, induc'd them all to be ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the matter; which was done with ſo much forwardneſs, that <hi>Tilleul,</hi> who was charg'd with the Treaſure, was not able to receive and weigh the Silver faſt enough.</p>
            <p>The Convents only were of the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they were exempted from this Search, under the Article of the Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that they ſhould be preſerv'd; by this means they quietly kept both their own Money, and what was confided to them. I order'd that Article to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd to them, to the end they might know, that the preſervation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, conſiſted, in not permitting them to be deſtroy'd; but as to the Money, I had in formal Terms, reſerv'd that to my ſelf: Otherwiſe they might have got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all the Riches of the City into their Houſes, to have depriv'd me of it. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe Reaſons, ſeveral of them continu'd ſo obſtinate, and among
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:103058:57"/>
the reſt, Father <hi>Grenelli</hi> a Jeſuit, the Guardian, and Procurator of the <hi>Corde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> that I was forc'd to have them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd, and to threaten them with worſe uſage. The Rector of the Jeſuits obey'd, and brought about Twenty thouſand Crowns in Gold, that he found in the Chamber of Father <hi>Grenelli,</hi> and about as much from the whole Houſe beſides; and then deſired, that I would order the Houſe to be every-where viſited, by which Conduct he engag'd me to releaſe his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious. So ſoon as the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were brought, who have a particular Talent at diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hidden Treaſures, they proteſted, they were ready to reveal all they had, ſo the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> retired; but when they were gone, the Reverend Fathers fell into their firſt Silence; in ſhort, I reſolv'd to charge the Captains with the Care of ſearching the Religious Houſes, to the end the Preſence of theſe principal Officers might preſerve all neceſſary Order and Reſervedneſs. This Search produc'd enough to make amends for the trouble it gave us; and in regard to the Churches, prevented even the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Profanation. After I had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely commanded 'em not to touch any of the ſacred Veſſels, or any thing apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Sacrifice, I order'd our
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:103058:58"/>
Chaplains to gather up what was only for the Decoration of the Churches. Father <hi>Paul,</hi> a <hi>Dominican,</hi> who hath (by I know not what Authority) given himſelf a ſort of a Miſſion among the <hi>Buccaniers;</hi> and uſually living upon the Coaſt, had follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Army, and put himſelf among our Chaplains; aided them with a mighty Zeal to execute my Orders, which ſeem'd to him ſufficiently juſt, in relation to the other Convents; but when he was to go to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> ſupported with the Credit of <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> he thought to have prevented this Viſit; but ſeeing there was no great Notice taken firſt of his Threats, nor afterwards of his Prayers, was then tranſported with horrour at the profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and came running to denounce up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, from God Almighty, the Anger of Heaven; yet they did not forbear going on with the Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>Altho' the Silver was brought in great abundance to the Contadore; that is, the Town-Houſe, where I had my Quarters; yet we did not receive, by much, what we might have expected. We had ſcarce got to the Coaſt of St. <hi>Martha,</hi> which I had been told was a Deſert, but they were acquainted with it at <hi>Carthagena;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe inform'd by three ſeveral Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:103058:58"/>
from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> of all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, they were amply acquainted with my Project, my Forces, and, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the time I ſhould get thither; ſo they begun to beſtir themſelves upon that very Alarm: All the Women, of any Quality, with their Jewels, the Nuns, and what was worſt of all, 120 Mules laden with Gold, went out in four Days time; they retir'd to <hi>Monpos,</hi> a Town forty Leagues from thence; and altho' we had not miſcarried in our firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, to attempt <hi>Noſtre Dame de la Poup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,</hi> yet we could not have got thither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the greateſt part of thoſe Treaſures was gone. However, the Honour which his Majeſty's Arms acquir'd in this occaſion, beſides near upon Eight or Nine Millions that could not eſcape us, comforted us for the loſs of the reſt.</p>
            <p>There is, in the Year, one intemperate Seaſon, that never miſſes this part of the <hi>Indian</hi> Coaſt, and it ſeem'd, as if the great Rains, and Thunder, which are the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of it, had, for a time deſiſted, to afford us the Opportunity of taking <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena;</hi> for no ſooner were we in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it, but the Air became infected: Eight hundred Men, in ſix Days time, were ſeiz'd with a contagious Diſtemper,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:103058:59"/>
of whom the greateſt part died; and, in a little time, we were ſcarce able to receive into the Hoſpital, which was with much Expedition eſtabliſhed, the great Number that was brought from all parts, every Day were we informed of ſome melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Example; all Ideas of Triumphs and Treaſures, were effac'd, by thoſe of Sickneſs and Mortality. In ſhort, if the Diſtemper had continued with this Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, I muſt have beheld my inevitable Ruine in the faireſt Port of the World, and no Enemy near me; not only have loſt the Fruits of all our Labours, but likewiſe the Squadron entruſted to me.</p>
            <p>There was a Report ſpread about, the Author of it I did not find out until ſome Days afterwards, That I could not carry back the King's Ships, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of the <hi>Buccaniers;</hi> who being accuſtom'd to theſe Climates, were no more infected with the Unhealthineſs of the Air, than the Natives that are very rarely touch'd with it. In this Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> that conceal'd his Spite at <hi>Hihimani,</hi> where he was retired, ſent to me, by his Major, a Writing, inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, That his Colony was in danger of being deſtroyed, in caſe the Enemies ſhould attempt a Deſcent there, which
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:103058:59"/>
was no ways to be doubted; that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of me the Forces I had drawn from thence; and in caſe of refuſal, he thereby made me reſponſible for all Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents. I anſwered by the ſame way, That his Colony was as much recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to me, as it had been to him; that concurring to his Sentiments, as to that Matter, I did conſent, whatſoever Inconveniency might attend the weakning of my ſelf by his departure, that he might return with three parts of his <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> all the Inhabitants, and part of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes; and, that what I kept with me, would therefore be too inconſiderable for the Coaſt to ſuffer by it. This Anſwer, which I deſigned with ſincerity, happen'd to be contrary to what he expected, he did not imagine I could have taken that Reſolution, thinking, by the Report ſpread about, to have made me ſo well compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the occaſion I ſhould have for the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> as to have determin'd my ſelf againſt their return; but ſeeing my firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he begun to be more compliant, and better diſpos'd, without ſpeaking of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away; and thereby plainly ſhewed us, what ſort of Intereſt detained him at <hi>Carthagena.</hi> As the Silver was brought in, ſo it was immediately carried on Board the King's Ships; upon which he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:103058:60"/>
               <hi>Daunou</hi> to acquaint me, That the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> were diſguſted, that I did not call ſome of them to be Witneſſes of what paſs'd at the Contadore; and propos'd to have me admit ſome Body from them. I found ſo much Inſolence in this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that I ſuſpected from whence it proceeded: I told <hi>Daunou,</hi> That if he happen'd to charge himſelf with any more ſuch Commiſſions, I would make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent it. I was at that inſtant inform'd, That ſome of the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> contrary to my Prohibition of pillaging Houſes, had broke through the Roof of a Houſe, and ſtole ſome Merchandizes: I took my Guards, and went through all the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the City, reſolv'd to make an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe who fell into my Hands; but they were all retired to the Poſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned them, where they received all the Threats I made them with a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Submiſſion: Moreover, I was not ſo ill ſerv'd by my Spies, as not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, that the ſeditious Diſcourſes they ſometimes held, upon the Silver being carried on Board the King's Ships, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd into them, by People wholly aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd to their own Intereſt, who took all Opportunities to expreſs their own Thoughts with the Tongues of the <hi>Bucca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:103058:60"/>I was not ſo much a Stranger to the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> Courage, as to apprehend any manner of Attempt from that part; but a Rumour being underhand whiſper'd, that they had a mind to pillage the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadore, to ſecure the ſhare they pretended to of the Booty; I was apprehenſive, leaſt they might force me to puniſh them ſo, that I ſhould not be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any farther Service from them, and I might poſſibly have occaſion for their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance on Board the King's Ships, in my return to <hi>France.</hi> Upon this I proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a Method which ſeem'd moſt likely to ſatisfie them, without engaging me to an unbecoming Condeſcenſion: I liberally recompens'd ſuch of the <hi>Bucca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers</hi> as were wounded, and gave more to the lam'd; there being ſo few of the one, or the other, that I could not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by much prejudice the Intereſts of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament; I order'd very conſiderable Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications to their Captains, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that had diſtinguiſh'd themſelves; I thought by the kindneſs I ſhewed to <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> and his Adherents, which were ſo exceſſive, that I am aſham'd to own it; I thought, I ſay, to have engag'd them to have made no farther Pretenſions; but I was ſurpriz'd to find, that by his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:103058:61"/>
of the eight Millions, he rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd two of them belong'd to the <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniers;</hi> and of theſe two Millions, he eſteem'd himſelf ſure of one; for he ſhares with them as Captain-General, as firſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain of each Frigat, as Proprietor of the Frigats of which he lends ſome to them, and lets them have others belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King, which with divers Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts he detains upon the Coaſts, at exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant Intereſt. When I was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Particulars, I reſolv'd with my Authority and Diligence to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate my ſelf out of this Affair: But this Diligence was the difficult Matter, a great part of the Equipage neceſſary in a Siege, which we had brought from the Fleet, was yet aſhoar, the Diſtempers depriv'd me of half my Men, and I had ſcarce got on Board half of the Silver. The Braſs Cannons of <hi>Carthagena</hi> were yet on the Ramparts; I entreated the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> to undertake this Work, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd; and I was inform'd, they had not only reſolv'd not to work, but likewiſe to make neither Watch or Ward, until they were put into poſſeſſion of their ſhare of the Booty. I ſhew'd no Concern at this time, but prevailing by Dint of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, upon the ſmall Number I had in a Condition of working, to uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:103058:61"/>
Efforts, I got on Board my Squadron all the Cannon of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> all that remain'd of what was brought on Shoar; and part of the Baſtions being already thrown down, on the 25th of <hi>May</hi> the Powder was put to the other Mines; I re-embark'd all my Troops, and my ſelf, leaving <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> his Officers, and <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> in the City; I acquainted both the one and the other, That if they pillag'd the leaſt of the Houſes I had mark'd, I would inſtantly fire their Frigates: They were too well laden, to ſuffer them to be expos'd to the Effects of my Threats, for having reſolv'd not to bring any Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes on Board the King's Ships, that I might be in a better Condition of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I did permit the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> to take what belong'd not to the Inhabitants that remained in the Town. <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> wrote me word, That he would anſwer for the Obedience of the <hi>Buccaniers;</hi> adding withal, That if their Conduct was any ways to be blam'd, it proceeded from that Severity which was us'd to them, in not letting them know what they were to expect of the Booty. He might have ſaid with more Truth, that it was his own Inquietude; and in reality, for ſome Days paſt, he had continually complain'd againſt the embarking of all the Silver;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:103058:62"/>
which, he ſaid, they could not tell how to get from the King's Ships: But yet, that he could not believe I would deprive him of any thing that ſo juſtly belong'd to him; having engag'd my ſelf by Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to let the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> divide Man for Man, with the Seamen of the King's Ships. He had a great deal of Reaſon to inſiſt upon this Writing; which was what I ever deſign'd to have obſerv'd; but when I underſtood, that by his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, Two of the Eight Millions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to him, I was ſurpriz'd at his meaning, believing him inform'd, as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body elſe was, that what appertain'd to the Seamen of the King's Ships, and conſequently to the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> whom I had receiv'd upon theſe expreſs'd Terms, was the Tenth of the Firſt Million, and the Thirtieth of all the others; which his Majeſty had been pleas'd to grant to the ſaid Men on Board his Ships, to excite them to do well, and as a Recompence for their Services, as it was explain'd in the Conditions upon which his Majeſty had conſented to this Armament. At length, altho' <hi>Du Tilleul</hi> was Night and Day employ'd in the Receipt, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barking of the Silver, and the infinite Particulars appertaining to a great Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, had not the time to examine his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:103058:62"/>
Books, and conſequently we could not exactly know what Silver there was; yet I ſo preſs'd him to make an Eſtimate of the whole Affair, to ſatisfie <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> and his Cabal, what did belong to them, that he made out the Account, and ſigned it.</p>
            <p>Upon the 29th I ſent this Account to <hi>Du Caſſe;</hi> who, upon my reiterated Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that I had ſent him, was at laſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd with his <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> and come down pretty near to the Fort of <hi>Bocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chica;</hi> below which was the whole Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, except the <hi>Scepter,</hi> who through the Ignorance of the Pilots, was got be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Banks, upon which ſhe had ſtruck, and had not then got clear of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> was extreamly ſurpriz'd upon the reading of the Account, wherein he ſaw that his, and the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> Shares, amounted only to about 40000 Crowns. He reckon'd, that the whole would have been divided into Four equal Parts, and he being very near a Fourth of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, one of theſe Parts would conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall to his Share: But when he opened his Eyes, and ſaw that dividing Man for Man with the King's Ships, ſignified ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of what appertain'd to the ſaid Ships
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:103058:63"/>
Companies, but not what appertain'd to the King, and the Armatures; and when it appear'd, that the part of the Ships Companies conſiſted in the Tenth of the Firſt Million, and the Thirtieth of the others; of which the Fourth, that might belong to him, amounted only to 40000 Crowns, he fell into ſuch a Rage, that not conſidering, that the leaving of his Government, without a Permiſſion from Court, and upon a particular Intereſt, was by all manner of Laws, a Criminal Action; yet he reſolv'd to ſteer for <hi>France;</hi> probably to demand Juſtice of himſelf, for being miſtaken; for as to any thing elſe, there cannot appear any pretence of Complaint. I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I was a long time before I could comprehend, that his Miſapprehenſion ſhould carry him ſo far, as to imagine, that the Credit of ſo many People was us'd, much Addreſs employ'd, great Sums of Money collected and expended, and ſo long a Voyage undertaken, to give the Fourth of what it produced, to the Governour of S. <hi>Domingo,</hi> and a Troop of <hi>Banditti;</hi> who without being at any Charge, and only for about ſix Weeks, at leaſt the greateſt part of them, idle Spectators of a great Action; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks Juſtice ſeems ſo repugnant to ſuch
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:103058:63"/>
a Thought, that <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd entertaining it. By allowing a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and Share, as I did to this Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they received too much Honour, eſpecially being joyn'd in the Diviſion with the Companies of the King's Ships, whoſe continual Service, which they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the King, and the State, ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly diſtinguiſh them from that baſe kind of Life that the others lead. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I do not ſee what Reply can be made to this Argument: If they are the King's Subjects, they were order'd to ſerve in this Enterprize, upon which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty did not declare there ſhould be any Diſtinction in favour of them; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Orders, the whole Strength of the Colony was to joyn the Forces I brought from <hi>France;</hi> and if they did not, I was to treat them as Rebels: And I was much in the wrong, to aſſociate them to the Conſideration that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to the King's faithful Subjects.</p>
            <p>When I was getting under Sail, to come out of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> I was forc'd to ſet on fire the Bomb-Galliot, her Maſts and Hulk were ſo ſhatter'd, that ſhe was not in a Condition of going to Sea. I left alſo the <hi>Providence</hi>-Brigantine, (of whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany there was not one Man capable of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:103058:64"/>
Service) with a <hi>Buccanier</hi>-Captain, until farther Order. The neceſſity I was in, of diſmounting ſome Ship, to afford ſome aſſiſtance to the others, by dividing of her Company amongſt them, had engag'd me to have fir'd the <hi>Christ</hi>-Ship, if <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> to whom it was neceſſary I ſhould give a Ship, to tranſport his People to the <hi>French</hi> Cape, had not been contented with that; which he arm'd as well as he could, to carry back the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and Negroes, to St. <hi>Domingo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 30th I was taken ſo very ill with the Diſtemper, that all that I could do, before I fell into a Condition that depriv'd me of my Intellect, was to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint <hi>Levy,</hi> that I committed the Care of the Squadron to him; and that he ſhould ſteer his Courſe for Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> according to the Reſolution he knew I had taken, to return from thence to <hi>France,</hi> without touching at <hi>Petit Guaves,</hi> where, as I was inform'd, the Air was not infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leſs than at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> by which the reſt of our Men would have infallibly periſh'd: From that time, I order'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that paſs'd; but the Account that follows, <hi>Levy,</hi> and the Major-General, gave me in Writing, as likewiſe by Word of Mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:103058:64"/>Upon the laſt of the Month of <hi>May,</hi> compleating the Ruine of the Fort of <hi>Boccachica,</hi> where we had ſome Days been at work, <hi>Daunou,</hi> after many fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Attempts to ſpeak with me, went to them, and acquainted them, That the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> being enrag'd at the ſmall part I gave them of the Booty, had propos'd to board and plunder the <hi>Scepter;</hi> but that afterwards they were come to the Reſolution, to return and plunder <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena:</hi> And in reality, they perceiv'd at that Inſtant, the greateſt part of their Frigates making into the Port, to ſail to it: He ſaid further, that they had paſs'd under the Stern of the <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> where <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> was on Board, to whom they had declar'd their Deſign; and, that he had exhorted them, not to commit ſuch an Infraction of the Treaty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the City ſurrender'd; that he had likewiſe ſent his Major to endeavour to diſſwade them from it; that for his own part, it gave him ſo much trouble, that he deſired only a hundred Sea-men, with which he ſhould think himſelf ſtrong enough to prevent their Deſigns on the City.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:103058:65"/>All the Squadron was out at Sea, excepting the <hi>Scepter,</hi> who was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nearer to them; but in ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition by reaſon of the Diſtemper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sea-men, that we were very far from being able to make this Detachment; And altho' they might have been, yet how could it be poſſible, for a hundred Men, ſeveral Hours behind the <hi>Buccaniers,</hi> to prevent them from landing? The ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and true Motive of this Propoſition was palpably apparent; and accordingly <hi>Levy,</hi> and the Major-General, expreſs'd their Opinion very freely to <hi>Daunou,</hi> whoſe Paſſion increas'd upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt they ſhew'd him. Yet <hi>Levy,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to apply all the Remedy that was to be us'd, made all the haſte he could on Board the Frigate of <hi>Macary,</hi> being neareſt the Fort, and longer in getting ready than the other, and by that able to be reach'd, and by his Authority he made her come to an Anchor again, believing, that afterwards ſhe would not dare but to come out with the <hi>Scepter;</hi> yet this Ship being got through the paſſage, the Frigate was no longer afraid of being ſtopp'd by her Cannon; <hi>Macary</hi> having for ſome time follow'd us, ſuddenly tack'd about, and ſtood after the reſt of his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:103058:65"/>
Companions, after having conferr'd with <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> with whom he ſtayed moſt part of the Night.</p>
            <p>It looks as if <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> was entirely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of his Sence, in not more carefully covering his Connivance with the <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caniers,</hi> in their violating of an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Capitulation. The <hi>Pontchartrain,</hi> aboard which he was, and the <hi>Malouin</hi>-Frigate, that he could have commanded, were both of them among the <hi>Buccaniers</hi> Frigates, when they reſolv'd upon this Courſe; Why did he not go after them, on all ſides firing on them? Yet ſhooting ſo high, or ſo low, as not to do them any damage? He might have made it to have been believ'd, that he was no Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complice in this Perfidiouſneſs, and at the ſame time have juſtified to the World, that it was not by my Orders committed, being it would then have appear'd, that it was done by Mutiniers; whereas this ſcandalous Herd being, in appearance, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Command, as formerly, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reſponſible for their Conduct to the K. of <hi>Spain;</hi> who might, if I ſhould ever happen to fall into his Power, with ſome Juſtice, uſe me as a Breaker of Treaties: For what appears in ſum of this Action, is a Capitulation manifeſtly broken by the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:103058:66"/>
King's Army. It was plain to us, <hi>Du Caſſe</hi> only thought of making the beſt of his way to get firſt of all into <hi>France,</hi> quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Squadron without leave, and even without the knowledge of any one, he brought to all the Sails of the <hi>Pont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chartrain,</hi> and we heard no more of him until the Fourth of <hi>June.</hi> The Squadron left <hi>Boccachica</hi> on the Firſt, after having diſingag'd themſelves of the Misfortune which the <hi>Scepter</hi> and <hi>Fort</hi> had, in ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the firſt Night after their coming out, upon two Banks three Leagues from the Coaſt, whereby they were like to have been loſt. The Squadron after this, ſtood for Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> when a Veſſel from <hi>Petit Guaves</hi> brought us a Pacquet; he met <hi>Du Caſſe,</hi> to whom he had likewiſe deliver'd one, which was a Duplicate of that he had for me: They came from <hi>Robert,</hi> Intendant of the Iſles, who had diſpatch'd away a Bark to inform me, That upon the Twenty ſeventh of <hi>April,</hi> Thirteen <hi>Engliſh Men of War,</hi> of which Eight were Capital Ships, were arriv'd at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> where there were ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that it was not to be doubted but this was the Squadron, (as he had been inform'd from <hi>France</hi>) that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies was to ſend after me, to prevent the Execution of my Deſigns; that this
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:103058:66"/>
Squadron was not to make any ſtay at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> upon which I was to take my Meaſures. The Day before I left <hi>France,</hi> I was advis'd, that to whatſoever place I went, Admiral <hi>Nevil,</hi> with Fifteen <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Ships, was to follow me, ſo ſoon as they knew the Courſe I ſteer'd. Theſe Informations concurring with each other, we did not doubt of the arrival of that Squadron in the <hi>Indian</hi> Seas, as likewiſe that we muſt meet them: For their Courſe, of conſequence, if they were inform'd at <hi>Jamaica</hi> of our Succeſs at <hi>Carthagena,</hi> as it was very probable, would be to expect us at Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> there not being any likelihood that we ſhould return to <hi>France,</hi> without paſſing upon that Coaſt to take in freſh Proviſions, and leave the Men I had taken from thence. I was then a little recovered from the Extremity of my Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and upon this News I held the firſt Council of this Expedition; there was no diverſity of Opinions, all the Captains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing, that we ought to ſteer for the Gulf of the Streights of <hi>Bahama;</hi> that we ought to ſupply our want of Water, by the moſt extraordinary good Management of what we had; that there would be an opportunity of taking in more upon the Coaſt of <hi>Accadia,</hi> which was the moſt probable way of miſſing the Enemy, who
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:103058:67"/>
could not be gone to expect us there, knowing we had a more convenient paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage upon many Accounts. Upon this Reſolution we alter'd our Courſe that we were ſteering to <hi>Tiburon,</hi> for that of <hi>Bahama,</hi> which we continu'd until the Sixth. It may here be obſerv'd, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one ought to depend upon the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Reaſons, when Fortune is in the Scale: The Courſe of Cape <hi>Tiburon,</hi> our Ruine, in appearance, was free of all Danger, the Enemy paſs'd very wide of it; and the way of <hi>Bahama,</hi> ſo ſure in our Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, carried us into that between <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica,</hi> and <hi>Carthagena,</hi> which they then ſteer'd, and occaſion'd us to fall into the midſt of them in the Night, between the Sixth and the Seventh. Some Hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Day, I was inform'd, that from time to time, they perceiv'd Fires made in a Ship behind us; this Signal not being to be made by any of ours, we began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, it was ſome advanc'd Frigate of the Enemies, who inform'd them by her Fires, that ſhe followed us, and that by keeping after her, they could not loſe us. There was then no other Reſolution to be taken, than to wait for the Day; we did not know our ſituation, in relation to that of the Enemies, ſo by any other manner of working, we ſhould have run
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:103058:67"/>
the ſame Riſque, to have fallen in with them, as to have ſteer'd clear of them. The firſt appearance of Day preſented us with the Image of an inevitable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Misfortune; we at firſt reckon'd Twenty Sail, then Twenty five, a little afterwards Twenty nine, and among them a Ketch. Eight of theſe Ships ſeem'd to be of an equal force to the <hi>Scepter,</hi> Ten or Twelve others, with the St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> the <hi>Furieux,</hi> and our other Ships of that Rate, the reſt with our Frigates from Thirty ſix to Forty four Guns; half of this Fleet was to Windward of our Squadron, and wanted but little of Cannon-ſhot of us; ſome others were exactly on our Lee; and the reſt, which were the great Ships before-mentioned, were in our Sterns, a little below us.</p>
            <p>Our great Misfortune was not only to have Eight and twenty Ships againſt our Seven Ships, and Three Frigates; but as an addition, our unfortunate Squadron was ſo ſtrangely weaken'd by the Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that ſhe was rather a general Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal for the reſt of the Officers, and Sea-men; inſomuch, that when we went to put our ſelves into a Condition of making ſome ſort of a reſiſtance, by the paleneſs of our Faces, and the weakneſs of our
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:103058:68"/>
Motion and Stirring, it look'd as if the Hoſpital of <hi>Paris</hi> was brought under Arms. To give an Idea of the Condition we were in, I need only ſay, that the other Ships were poſſibly in a much worſe Condition than the <hi>Scepter,</hi> who out of her Complement of 700 Men, had not above 350 that were able to take Arms, or work our Artillery. What an alteration for me in particular! My Expedition had acquir'd ſome Honour to the King's Arms, and would have produc'd conſiderable Advantages to my Armatures. The ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Carthagena</hi> ſeem'd to have acquir'd me a pleaſing Diſtinction; and being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd, I had, at my Return, a proſpect of Glory and Pleaſures, all which now paſs'd like a ſhadow; and I had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before my Eyes, the deſtruction of a flouriſhing Squadron, which I had the Honour to be entruſted with; the Diſpleaſure of the King and his Miniſters, in the Circumſtances of this Loſs, which not only depriv'd His Majeſty of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ships, but ſo much advantag'd his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and carried them thoſe Riches, that were in a manner ready to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd <hi>France;</hi> the Grief of my Armatures, for whom all was loſt by this unhappy Rencounter; and my continual Deſpair in the Remainder of a Life, which after
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:103058:68"/>
a long Impriſonment, I muſt have paſs'd in Obſcurity, if the Report of my bad Fortune had not render'd me remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Theſe were my Reflections, when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving acquainted all my People, that we ought to die like Men of Honour, I had two occaſions of being comforted; the firſt was, the Officers proteſting to me, with an Air of Aſſurance, that the Ships ſhould be defended, whilſt any of them were living; and the Ships Company en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ſame Sentiment; inſomuch, that the Sick, at leaſt thoſe not at extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſhew'd themſelves as forward as the others; ſo I beheld Reſolution on all ſides of me. The other was, ſo ſoon as the Signal for the Order of Battle was made, the <hi>St. Lewis, Furieux, Verman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dois, St. Michael,</hi> and the <hi>Mutine,</hi> came up ſo faſt, and fell ſo well into their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they allow'd us no occaſion of doubting of their having the ſame Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ours; the <hi>Fort,</hi> the <hi>Apollo, L'A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and <hi>Marin,</hi> did not obey the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but kept to Windward, where they chanc'd to be; the Captains of the two laſt were ſick, and I had taken from them the greateſt part of their Men, to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the great Ships, and had deſign'd
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:103058:69"/>
them for Fire-ſhips; but not having time to fit them up for it, nor to fetch away their Sick, they were become altogether uncapable of any Service, ſo I could no ways wonder they did not fall into their order'd Station; as to the <hi>Fort,</hi> and the <hi>Apollo,</hi> I was apprehenſive that the firſt had loſt ſo many of her Men, that ſhe was not able to make any ſort of a Fight; the other being her Second, did believe, as it is the Cuſtom, that ſhe was not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon her Flag, <hi>Du Buiſſon,</hi> by the Death of the Vicount <hi>Coetlogon,</hi> then car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Flag of Rear-Admiral. At this inſtant, one of the Enemies Ships having fir'd a Gun upon the Fly-boat, called, <hi>The City of Amſterdam,</hi> who was a good way a-ſtern of us; ſhe ſtruck Sail, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd: They found a great many ſick Men on Board her, and a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable quantity of Ammunition and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. The only <hi>Traverſier</hi> left me had the ſame Deſtiny with the Fly-boat, with whom ſhe was. But while theſe things paſs'd, we found that half of their Fleet, who in a little time were got within reach of us, were unwilling to engage, until the others to Leeward could come to the Action: Yet being unwilling to hand in their Sails, to ſtay for the others behind, they kept themſelves in a Line, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:103058:69"/>
us to get before them. We per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by their working, that we were yet to have ſome Hours of quiet, and none of us being ſtrong enough to ſupport a long Action, we repos'd our ſelves in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the Event. About two a Clock in the Afternoon, the Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral came to me, and told me, There was no farther hopes of delays, that the advanc'd part of the Enemies Fleet was got within leſs than Cannon-ſhot, and to Windward of our Squadron, and their great Ships exact a-broadſide of our Lee. This being ſo, the Signal general for the Order of Battle was given, without loſs of time; I added to it the particular Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of the <hi>Fort,</hi> to bring her to her Station; but ſhe only did ſo much as was neceſſary, to let us know that ſhe knew her Signal, and then ſtanding to Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſhe confirm'd me in the Thoughts I had in the Morning.</p>
            <p>The Affair was ſufficiently ſerious to keep us attentive: We obſerv'd firſt of all, that the Ships which might have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd us, choſe rather to ſlacken their way, and fell from us; with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding of them, I was partly of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that it was by going larger away than we who kept cloſe to the Wind, that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:103058:70"/>
their great Ships had gain'd ſo much upon us. The fear of deceiving my ſelf in this matter, made me conſult all thoſe that I reckon'd able to inform me; and they all being of the ſame Opinion, I eaſily pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated into the Thoughts of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral, who reckon'd there was no Safety for me, but to go before the Wind, for the Streights of <hi>Bahama;</hi> ſo he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to get ſo much a Head of me, as to hinder my paſſage; but I perceiv'd at the ſame time, that he might be miſtaken in his working; becauſe, inſtead of ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parallel to the Courſe we ſteer'd, his coming up opened an Angle; which in truth, brought him into my Traverſe, but in reality at a greater diſtance than when he was a little a-ſtern of us; therefore by tacking about, I ſhould be at a greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than I was before; beſides, I was ſure to get ſomething by it.</p>
            <p>I was certain, that the Ships which might have attack'd me, durſt not do it, and therefore it would not much trouble me, if I did find them in my paſſage. Upon this, I ſent the <hi>Marine</hi>-Frigate, to order all the Ships of the Squadron to tack about, preciſely, at the ſhutting in of Night; that I would light no Fires, nor make any Signal, and that they ſhould
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:103058:70"/>
go as cloſe haul'd to the Wind as it was poſſible. At the time appointed we went about, but we were too near the Enemy to conceal our working from them; one of their ſmall Frigates being likewiſe got in amongſt us, I was oblig'd to give him ſome Cannon-ſhot from the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and the <hi>Furieux,</hi> who was ſomething nearer to him; with which he ſtood ſo corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that we ſaw him no more afterwards. But the different Signals which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Ships made by Fires to each other, aſſur'd us, that they who were moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, communicated to them behind what paſs'd, ſo we doubted not of our being follow'd. However, the next Day, ſo ſoon as it was light, we found the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of our working; for we could only reckon 14 Ships, who follow'd us in a Line one after the other, and not ſo nigh by far as the Day before; but at the ſame time we miſs'd the <hi>Fort, Apollo, L'Avenant, Marin,</hi> and the <hi>Diep</hi> Flyboat: We having not heard any Cannon-ſhot, we could not think they were taken: However, it was not until the next Day that I was eas'd of this Apprehenſion, by report of the <hi>Mutine,</hi> that rejoin'd me, acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, That when ſhe carried the Orders for the Ships to go about, thoſe we miſs'd being conſiderably to Windward of us,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:103058:71"/>
who had by much the Wind of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies when we tack'd, it was much eaſier for them to get clear, by keeping on their way, than in following me: <hi>Simonet</hi> added, that the <hi>Fort</hi> had loſt her Foretop-maſt: But having ſeen all the Enemies Ships ſtanding as we did, at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from each other, there was no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear that ours were purſued.</p>
            <p>This ſeparation being not to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, my Thoughts were wholly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the preſervation of the reſt of the Squadron, and to make uſe of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I had got; I continu'd the ſame Board, until within twenty Leagues of <hi>Carthagena,</hi> where we were on the 9th of the ſame Month of <hi>June.</hi> In the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I made the Signal of holding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Courſe; and when it was quite dark, I acquainted the other Ships, with three Guns, that they were to ſteer Weſt, directly before the Wind: There was then but three of the Enemies Ships that kept within ſight of us, and they were a great way from us; they could not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine what this Signal mean'd, and ſo kept on the ſame Board. In the mean while, we ran this Night 22 Leagues, and the next Day found our ſelves perfectly out of all Buſineſs on that ſide. But to one
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:103058:71"/>
Trouble ended, commonly comes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: It was not poſſible for us to reach <hi>Bahama,</hi> by holding through the uſual paſſage, that lies between <hi>Cuba</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica,</hi> and which is not at all dangerous; but we were oblig'd to take that to the Southward, terrible for the Shelves, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which we were forc'd to paſs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' we were altogether ignorant of them; however, ſupplying the want of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with our utmoſt Care and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, we eſcap'd all the Rocks, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving doubled the Cape of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> found our ſelves on the 26th in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Streight of <hi>Bahama;</hi> where we underſtood by a ſmall <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſel, who fell into our Squadron, coming from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> laden with Indigo and Cotton, to the value of about 25000 Crowns, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet we had met was commanded by <hi>Nevil,</hi> and was compos'd, at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> of 13 Ships that came from <hi>England,</hi> of three that were in the Iſland, and eight <hi>Hollanders,</hi> of which four were very large Ships, and came out of the Streights, who made in all 24 Men of War, to whom were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing four Fire-ſhips, and a Ketch: Which was exactly the Number we had ſeen; their Intention was to have ſtayed 24 Hours only at <hi>Jamaica,</hi> but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:103058:72"/>
Winds had detained them eight Days; that their Ships were in good Health, but very ill mann'd, the greateſt of them not having above 350 Men, and thoſe of between 50 and 60 Guns, 150 Men: This laſt Circumſtance diminiſh'd the admiration I was in, that none of them who could have attack'd me, had not begun the Fight by engaging of me, until ſuch time as the reſt could get up to them; it may be, they were ignorant of the ill ſtate we were reduc'd to by Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or poſſibly they did not give Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what they might have known by the <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Flyboat; for the Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that we ſhewed them, was no ways anſwerable to what ſhe could have told them.</p>
            <p>Having detach'd away the <hi>Mutine</hi>-Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat for St. <hi>Domingo,</hi> with the Forces, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and Negroes, that were on Board that part of the Squadron then with me, we ſteer'd on our Courſe; nothing material happen'd to us, excepting an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in our Reckoning: For we were got to the Eaſtward of <hi>Newfoundland,</hi> when we thought we had been to the Weſtward; which oblig'd us to go into <hi>Conception</hi>-Bay for Water, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to have taken at <hi>Plaicentia:</hi> We
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:103058:72"/>
came to an Anchor on the Fourth of the Month of <hi>August,</hi> having only ſix Days Water on Board. The Captain of a ſmall Veſſel coming from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which we took on the Second Inſtant, did us very good Service in our Anchorage, which we did not know; but this Veſſel which the <hi>Vermandois</hi> mann'd, happend to loſe the Squadron in a Miſt; as did alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall Veſſel, that we found aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd at Sea, upon which we ſent likewiſe ſome Men, and ſince we never heard more of them. The great want of ſome freſh Proviſions, oblig'd me to ſend the Captain of the Prize, taken at <hi>Bahama,</hi> to propoſe to ſome Fiſher-men, retir'd to the bottom of the Bay, called <hi>La Carbonniere,</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply me with what Cattle they could, and to lend me their Boats to take in Water; upon which I promis'd, to do them no harm. They anſwer'd me by the ſame Meſſenger, That they had ſcarce any freſh Proviſions; but they would give me what they had, and accommodate me with their Boats; provided, I gave them Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtages. The aſſiſtance was not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable enough, to accept it upon this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; ſo I reſolv'd to burn a dozen, or fourteen, pitiful Houſes that were there, after I had taken in my Water.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:103058:73"/>In the mean time, I was informed by a Priſoner, That there were eight <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War at St. <hi>John</hi>'s, eight Leagues from us; ſent thither for the Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of that Colony, ruined by the Governour of <hi>Plaicentia;</hi> that theſe Ships, whereof two carried 70 Guns each, and the reſt from 50 to 60, had brought 13 Foot-Companies, commanded by <hi>Gibſon,</hi> Lieutenant-Governour of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> who were to ſtay there; that <hi>Norris</hi> command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Fleet; and, that in a Council of War, held at our arrival, it was reſolv'd, to ſtand out to fight us. This News made us double our Diligence to get in the Water we wanted, and to prepare our ſelves, not only to fight the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but to ſeek them out. To this purpoſe we got under Sail; on the Seventh of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> we ſtood to <hi>La Carbonniere,</hi> to burn the little Houſes; but the Weather being ſo bad, that we could not get to them without danger, beſides the inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of the place, rendering this Action not ſufficiently important, to conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way time upon it, I took the Party to go before St. <hi>John</hi>'s, to attack the Enemies, if they had been out; but apparently, ſome reflection of the force and largeneſs of our Ships, had prevented them from
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:103058:73"/>
coming out, and the Port was ſo ſtreight, as to render any Attempt upon them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable; I was contented to ſhew my ſelf, and offer them Battle, which ſeeing they did not Anſwer we ſteer'd for the Coaſt of <hi>France</hi> upon the Eighth of the ſame Month of <hi>August:</hi> and on the Twenty fourth of the ſaid Month, in the Fourth Degree of Latitude, and . . Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, we perceiv'd ſix Ships cruiſing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly in the Courſe we ſteer'd. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the weakneſs to which we were reduc'd, our Ships not having then by much, one half of our Complement of Men; the Number of the Enemies, ſuppoſing they were ſo, did no ways oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion us to fear meeting them; beſides, this place not being a uſual cruiſing ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with them; and on the contrary, very common for the <hi>French</hi> Ships; there was a great deal of appearance that they were ſuch, and many Conveniences would attend this joining; ſo I continu'd on my way: But when I came up with them, three of them appear'd to be three Deck Ships, the fourth equal to ours of 64 Guns, a Frigate of 40 Guns, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall Veſſel, that did not bring her ſelf into the Line; whilſt we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering of what Country they were, and had brought our ſelves into Order of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:103058:74"/>
with the Wind upon the Beam, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame Method which they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in expecting us, they put forth <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours, and contrary to the Cuſtom of that Nation, they did not fire firſt, altho' we were in leſs than Cannon-ſhot. We put forth our Colours, at the ſame time they ſhewed theirs; and to do them Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, it was impoſſible to make a bolder working than what they ſhewed; little did they gueſs the badneſs of our Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor that the <hi>Scepter,</hi> St. <hi>Lewis, Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieux, Vermandois,</hi> and St. <hi>Michael,</hi> were reduc'd to the weakneſs of 40 Gun Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, not knowing theſe Circumſtances, it muſt be allowed that they ſhew'd a great deal of Reſolution.</p>
            <p>We were ſo far advanc'd, that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of His Majeſty's Arms would not permit us to turn back, but rather to make our ſelves a paſſage; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that Attempt which would infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have diſcovered our weakneſs, would as certainly have encourag'd the Enemy, upon whom we came within the reach of a Fuſil <hi>Boucanniere,</hi> where we then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd their Beds and Hamocks to be paſs'd from the Forecaſtle to the Quarter-deck, to cover them from our ſmall Shot; this hindered us from diſcerning the ſpace
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:103058:74"/>
between the Forecaſtle and Quarter-deck, and occaſion'd us to believe them Three-deck-ſhips; it was eaſie to miſtake them, three being of thoſe great Frigates of 72 Guns, which have that length, width, and depth, ſo they wanted only ſome Beams and Planks to unite them; the fourth was ſomething leſs, and about the ſtrength of the <hi>Furieux;</hi> the fifth a Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate of 40 Guns: The Commander was in the midſt of his Squadron, and my ſelf alſo in the Center of His Majeſty's Ships, both ſides being exactly in a Line, I was only to ſpring my Loofe to come a-broadſide of him, and upon my Signal the Fire began, which continu'd from half an Hour after Three, until Seven; and with much more briskneſs on our ſide, than I could have expected from our weakneſs; the Enemy, altho' better provided, in my Opinion, ſhewed not altogether ſo much; however, they kept as cloſe to the Wind as it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the Fight began, they ſet their Sails as we did, that is, ſo as to continue on the Courſe upon which we found them, which was North North-Weſt, a very contrary Courſe to what I
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:103058:75"/>
was to ſteer, and from which I could not depart; ſo I went about in our Line of Battle, to leave the Cape to the Eaſt.</p>
            <p>In the execution of this, the Fire was pretty violent on both ſides; but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, inſtead of going about, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued their Broadſides, which paſs'd in a moment, and we got far enough to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any farther damage. In a very little while afterwards, the Enemies went about likewiſe all at once; yet I was fully perſwaded, they would not endeavour to begin the Fight again, by reaſon they continu'd their lower Sails furl'd as well as we, who wrought with much trouble through the want of Hands to repair the great damage we ſuffered in our Sails and Rigging: For as to the Men, there was not abroad the <hi>Scepter</hi> above eleven killed and wounded, and in the other Ships yet leſs in proportion; but the <hi>Vermandois</hi> having loſt her Foretop-maſt, I was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly troubled, becauſe I did not think her able to get up another; yet ſhe did not only attempt it in the Night, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly accompliſhed it early the next Day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:103058:75"/>We continu'd our Courſe all Night, with an eaſie Sail, and our uſual Lights. The next Day we were in a Condition to have begun again, if the Enemy had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed us; which we doubted of in the Night, as not diſcerning any of their Lights; but it is probable, that they had not leſs work to repair than we had, ſo I preſume they ſpent the Night at work, and the next Day we were almoſt out of fight.</p>
            <p>We had done our Buſineſs, which was to paſs without ſhame: We had no Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to expect from a ſecond En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement; but on the contrary, many Inconveniences, and one almoſt inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; which was, that the Squadron would periſh at Sea for want of Proviſions, if any endamag'd Ship ſhould conſiderably detain us. Therefore we kept on our way, and the Enemies followed us until the 26th at Noon, at which time they went about to the other Board.</p>
            <p>I cannot refuſe making the Officers and Seamen the Acknowledgments I owe them; for they did, in this occaſion, by much go beyond their Strength; and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:103058:76"/>
with the Good-will they expreſs, if our Force had been ſomething leſs unequal, the Enemies would have had more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to have diſengag'd themſelves. We came at laſt into <hi>Brest,</hi> upon the 29th of <hi>August,</hi> 1697.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103058:76"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>Sam. Buckley,</hi> at the <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VOyages and Diſcoveries in <hi>South-Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica:</hi> The firſt up the River of <hi>Amazons</hi> to <hi>Quito</hi> in <hi>Peru,</hi> and back again to <hi>Brazil</hi> performed at the Command of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by <hi>Chriſtopher D'Acug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> The Second up the River of <hi>Plate,</hi> and thence by Land to the Mines of <hi>Poto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,</hi> by Monſieur <hi>Acarete.</hi> The Third from <hi>Cayenne</hi> into <hi>Guiana,</hi> in ſearch of the Lake of <hi>Parima,</hi> reputed the richeſt Place in the World. By M. <hi>Grillet</hi> and <hi>Bechamel.</hi> Done into <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the Originals, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Accounts of thoſe Parts hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto extant. The whole illuſtrated with Notes and Maps. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Account of Monſieur <hi>de la Salle</hi>'s laſt Expedition and Diſcoveries in <hi>North-America.</hi> Preſented to the <hi>French</hi> King, and publiſhed by the Chevalier <hi>Tonti,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of Fort St. <hi>Louis,</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of the <hi>Iſlinois.</hi> Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> from
<pb facs="tcp:103058:77"/>
the <hi>Paris</hi> Original. Alſo the Adventures of the Sieur <hi>de Montauban,</hi> Captain of the <hi>French Buccaniers,</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Guinea,</hi> in the Year 1695. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>French Perfumer;</hi> teaching the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways of extracting the Odours of Drugs and Flowers, and making all the Compoſitions of <hi>Perfumes</hi> for Powder, Waſh-balls, Eſſences, Oyls, Wax, Poma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Paſte, <hi>Queen of Hungary's Water, Roſa Solis,</hi> and other Sweet Waters. The Manner of preparing <hi>Sweet Toilets, Boxes, &amp;c.</hi> with the Preparations and Uſe of Perfumes of all Kinds whatſoever. Alſo how to colour and ſcent Gloves and Fans. Together with the Secret of cleanſing To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco, and perfuming it for all ſorts of Snuff, <hi>Spaniſh, Roman,</hi> &amp;c. The Second Edition, Corrected. In <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Preſs, and will be finiſhed in a Month.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>John le Clerc</hi>'s Additional Notes to Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Paraphraſe and Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon all the Books of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, faithfully tranſlated to ſupply the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Edition of Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi> In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:103058:77"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
